（序曲）
西部开拓史
主演：卡洛贝克
主演：李柯伯
主演：亨利方达
主演：卡洛琳琼斯
主演：卡尔马登
主演：葛雷哥莱毕克
主演：乔治派伯
主演：劳柏普莱斯顿
主演：黛比雷诺
主演：詹姆斯斯图尔特
主演：伊莱沃勒
主演：约翰韦恩
主演：理查威麦
旁白：史宾塞屈赛
编剧：詹姆士韦伯
制片：伯诺史密斯
“南北战争”篇 导演：约翰福特
“铁路”篇 导演：乔治马歇尔
“河流、平原、非法之徒”篇 导演：亨利哈塞威拍
这个地方今日有个名字 并且在地图上有迹可寻
This land has a name today and is marked on maps.
但是这地名、地标、土地 全都是靠赢来的
But the names and the marks and the land all had to be won.
从大自然和土著手上赢得的
Won from nature and from primitive man.
五个世代之前 差不多一百二十五年前…
Five generations ago, a mere 125 years back...
大家只称这片土地为“西部”
...this land was known only as the West...
只有少数几个白人才知道这里
...known only to a handful of white men...
孤单的捕兽皮者在这片 广阔荒原里寻找海狸
...lonely trappers wandering its vastness in search of beaver.
这些人被称为山中居民 一群新世代的人
They were known as "mountain men", a new breed.
像吉姆布里哲 法兰屈瑞和萨柏特，奈勒斯罗林等人
Men like Jim Bridger, Linus Rawlings...
比印地安人更像印地安人 只差没印地安血统
...more Indian than the Indians in all but blood.
他们自订法律…
They held to no law but their own...
浮云游子，居无定所 永远不停地随处迁移
...drifted free as the clouds, settled nowhere, kept forever on the move.
带着长满茧的双足和未钉铁鞋的马 从不驻足于任何地方
Their mocassined feet and unshod horses left no trace on the land.
他们与那些和平相处的印地安人一样…
Like the Indians, with whom they were at peace...
他们除了自己找到的东西之外 其他什么都不要
...they wanted nothing beyond what they found and little of that.
群山…森林…荒野…
The mountains, the forests, the harsh country...
对他们而言，就像星星一样…
...were as unchanging to them as the stars...
永远都不会改变
...and just as unyielding.
在那群山和广阔平原遥遥之外…
Far behind the mountains, beyond the rolling plains...
他们离开了东部
...they had left the people of the East...
那些庸庸碌碌的人们
...people who were restless in another way.
（通往西部之关卡 伊利运河）
当他们看到高山时 便想到分水岭
The kind who would look at the mountain and see a watershed...
看到森林时 便想到用来盖屋子的木头
...look at the forest and see lumber for houses...
看到石头平原便想到农场
...look at a stony field and see a farm.
他们一心一意朝向西部迈进…
Their faces and their instincts had been turned to the West...
打从清教徒初次登陆美国之后
...ever since Plymouth Rock and James Town.
捕兽皮者跟随狼的行迹 或峡谷弯处前进…
The trapper's road was the trade of the wolf or the bend of the canyon.
但是携家带眷浩浩荡荡 追日前进…就必须有更宽阔的大路
But for whole families following the sun, there had to be broader ways.
但前进荒野没有陆路，只有水路
There were no roads into the woodlands, only rivers...
结果他们便跑错方向 要不往北，就是往南
...and they flowed in the wrong direction, north or south.
或者被挡在阿勒格尼山脚下
Or else they stopped at the Alleghanys.
直到有天
Until one day...
有个人发现一条新河流 这个人叫做度威克林顿
...a new river took source in the mind of a man named DeWitt Clinton.
他认为这条河流能通往西部
He conceived of a river that would go west.
结果美国人拿出他们冒险患难的精神 证实果然没错
And in the way Americans have of acting out their dreams, it came to be.
伊利运河从艾柏尼之上 离开赫德森…
The Erie Canal left the Hudson above Albany...
然后流通到五大湖
...and carried clear across to the Great Lakes.
那些向往开垦处女地 展开新生活的人们…
People who yearned for virgin land and the new life...
现在有一条快速水路带领他们  许多人络绎不绝
...now had a highway to take them. And they moved along.
《乌提卡之光号》开始登船！
Pride of Utica now loading.
（码头处）搭《乌提卡之光号》的人请登船！
All aboard for the Pride of Utica.
兰姆西一家！ 彼得史密斯！
The Ramsey family, Peter Smith...
史寇卡一家！
...the Skoga family...
全部八个人！
...all eight of 'em.
所有人请登上《乌提卡之光号》！
All aboard for the Pride of Utica.
因为你们家儿子的健康 才会想搬去西部？
Is the laddie's health the reason you're heading west?
有一部分是
Partly.
我们大部分原因是 东部的土地太多石头了
Only partly. Mostly our trouble East was rocks.
几年前我有一个农场 一亩地挖出一百桶石头
I had me a farm where some years I'd raise 100 bushels of rocks a year.
齐伯伦，你别乱骗人家
Zebulon, you hadn't oughta lie to the man like that.
老婆，我可是老实人 我告诉他的都是实话
Wife, I'm a God-fearing soul, and I tell the truth as I see it.
我从来不使用锄犁 我都拿火药炸出犁沟
I never used a plow. I'd blast out the furrows with gunpowder.
结果有天早上
Then one mornin'...
我把桶子从井里舀上来…
...I hauled the bucket up out of the well and...
结果那桶子里居然满满都是石头
...so help me, the bucket was full of rocks.
石头！
Rocks.
我站在那里 试图不口出秽言
I just stood there right still trying not to blaspheme...
我对自己说 “你儿子身体不好”
...and said to myself: "You've got a son that's ailin'.
“一个不肯出嫁的女儿”
"You've got a 20-year-old daughter who won't take a husband."
- 在那里，成天幻想做梦
There she sits, moonin' as usual.
- 爸
Pa.
“另一个女儿脑子不晓得在想什么”
"You've got another daughter, just don't seem quite right in the head."
莉莉丝？
Lilith.
什么事，爸？
Yes, Pa?
我告诉你啊…
I remind you, sir.
我站在那里 手中仍提着那装满石头的桶子…
I'm still standing there holding a bucket full of rocks...
呆呆看着它好久一段时间
...and staring into a bleak old age.
结果我便当场立誓说…
So I made me a vow right then and there. I said:
“如果我能找到一个身上有五百元 而且喜欢石头的人…”
"If I can find a man with $500 who likes rocks...
“那就让那个傻瓜来当 这农场的主人吧”
"...then there's gonna be another fool ownin' this farm."
结果上帝便派了那么一个人给我…
Well, sir, the Lord provided such a man...
现在我便在这里
...and here I am.
他根本就是唬你的 哈维先生
He ain't told you one word of truth, Mr. Harvey.
我们的农场是全镇最棒的
We had the best farm in the township.
是啊，整个“石头村”里最棒的 全都是石头！
Yeah, Rockville Township it was. Stone County.
喔，才不是呢！
Oh, it was not.
是他不安于室 才把我们一家子拖到这里
It was his itchin' foot that brought us here.
天晓得我们会在哪落脚
Heaven knows where we'll end up.
喔，这些是我的儿子们 安格斯，布鲁特斯和柯林
Oh, these are my laddies. Angus, Brutus and Colin.
- 你们好？ - 哈罗
-How do you do? -Hello.
他们好像已经和你们女儿认识了
I think they're already acquainted with your daughters.
- 他们都单身？
Be they single?
- 是的，目前都单身
Aye, single so far.
我开始觉得这伊利诺州很有意思唷！
Well, this Illinois country's beginning to sound better to me.
莉莉丝，过来唱首歌 给这几位小伙子听听
Lilith, strike up a little tune for these handsome lads.
- 喔，我没心情，爸
I ain't in no mood, Pa.
- 莉莉丝，平常可以耍脾气  现在可不准你！
Lilith, there's a time for coaxin'. This ain't the time.
好吧
All right.
一位住在海里费克斯的勇敢船长
"A captain bold in Halifax
在郡内落脚休息…
"Who lived in country quarters
背叛了一位女仆
"Betrayed a maid who hanged herself
有天早上她在房间里上吊自杀… 莉莉丝
-"One morning in her daughter's--" -Lilith!
你怎么唱这种不三不四的歌
Now, you know better than to sing a song like that.
- 你们知道什么歌？ - 我们知道《洋基大佬》
-What ones do you know? -We know "Yankee Doodle".
- 《洋基大佬》？ - 他们母亲早逝…
-"Yankee Doodle"? -Their mother's dead.
他们没学到什么社交礼仪
They haven't had much learnin' in the social graces since we left Scotland.
好吧，给他们唱 《家在草原上》吧
All right, give 'em "A Home in the Meadow".
【走，走，跟我走吧】
Away, away, come away with me
伊芙，来，你也一起唱
Eve, you, too.
【那荒野长着野草】 - 很好
Where the grass grows wild - That's it.
【而且风自由的吹】 - 来，加入
And the winds blow free - Come on, join in.
【走，走，跟我走吧】 - 很好，很好
Away, away, come away with me - That's it, that's it.
【我会和你在草地上安一个家】
"And I'll make you a home in the meadow
【来吧，来吧，有一片神奇的土地】
Come, come, there's a wondrous land
【为了充满希望的心】
For the hopeful heart
【荒野乐意帮助】
"For the willing hand
【来吧，来吧 ，有一片神奇的土地】
"Come, come, there's a wondrous land
【我将在这里为你在草地上建一个家】
Where I'll build you a home In the meadow"
搭《飞箭号》请上船！
Loading for the Flying Arrow.
所有搭《飞箭号》的人请上船！
All aboard for the Flying Arrow.
普莱斯考特家族！
The Prescott family.
我们在这里，快点
Here we be. Come on.
还有哈维及三个儿子！
Alex Harvey and three sons.
杰佛瑞罗斯及家人！
Jeffrey Rose and family.
【我有一个老骡子，她的名字叫贝尔】
"I've got an old mule and her name is Belle
【伊利运河十五英里】
"Fifteen miles on the Erie Canal
【她是走得非常慢的好朋友】
"She's a mighty slow worker But a good ole pal
【伊利运河十五英里】
"Fifteen miles on the Erie Canal
【驳船已拉了我们一天】
"We've pulled some barges in our day
【挤满了人，嘿！！！】
"Filled with people callin' 'hey'
【十五英里】
"Fifteen miles
【在伊利运河】
"On the Erie Canal! "
但运河只是前往希望之地的第一步
But the canal was only the first step toward the promised land.
接下来的阶段更为漫长艰辛
The next steps were longer and harder.
那些付得起更多船费的人 搭乘蒸汽船直达目的地
Those who could raise the fare went by steamboat to the end of the line.
其他人则透过较省钱的方式 前往俄亥俄州，伊利诺州…
Others found a cheaper way to head for Ohio, Illinois...
然后再往其他地方开垦发展
...and the open spaces beyond.
莉莉丝，莉莉丝，你听这个…
Lilith...listen to this:
“他们在林子里依依不舍地告别”
"Theirs was a poignant parting in the forest.
“年轻英俊的樵夫在树干上 刻出两颗心”
"The handsome young backwoodsman carved two hearts on a tree trunk...
“然后从十步处将刀射进 两颗心的交会处”
"...then from ten paces, hurled a knife at the junction of the two hearts."
交会处？什么东西？
Junction, what's that?
就是两颗心相印的地方 你再听…
Well, that's where the two hearts meet. Now, listen:
“他的刻工技法纯熟…”
"His marksmanship was uncanny.
“他连续三次都将刀子射中目标
"Three times he hurled the knife on target.
第一次他说代表幸运”
"'That was for luck', he said the first time.
“第二次刺中他说代表着深刻的 神圣的爱情”
"'That was for love, deep, divine love', he said the second.
“第三次代表着祈求一份
"And the third time, 'That was a prayer...
永远不消逝的爱情”
"'...a plea for love undying."'
是不是很美呢？
Isn't that beautiful?
是啊，如果真有人那样讲话的话
I reckon. If anybody ever talks like that.
重点是在感觉，不是那些话语
Well, it's the sentiments, not the talk.
你真的很奇怪耶，伊芙…
There ain't no sense to you, Eve.
你想当农夫老婆 但你却不肯嫁给农夫
You want to be a farm wife but you don't want to marry a farmer.
你也一样啊
Neither do you.
我当然不要
Of course not.
我才不要和农场扯上任何关系
I don't want to have nothin' to do with farms.
我要穿丝绸衣裳，坐华丽马车
I want silk dresses and fine carriages...
和一个味道高尚的男人
...and a man to smell good.
我想回东部，不是去西部
What I want's back East, not West...
我总有一天会去的，你看着好了
...and I'll get there yet. You watch.
你根本还不晓得自己要什么
You don't know what you want yet.
重点在于男人的特质 不是他住的地方
It's the man that counts, not where he lives.
- 准备好了吗？ - 准备好了
-Ready, man? -Ready.
爸爸！有人从下游来了
Daddy, somethin' comin' up river.
我猜是具敌意的印地安人
Hostile Indians, I expect.
- 会不会是河上海盗，齐伯伦？ - 不晓得
-Could it be river pirates, Zebulon? -Don't know.
听说正当的人不会在夜里 航行于这条河上
They say no honest man travels this river at night.
我只看到一个人，爸
I can only see one man, Pa.
听说那是海盗的惯用技俩 他们都躲在船里…
I hear that's a favorite pirate trick. They hide in the bottom of the boat...
等到接近时才发动突击
...till they're ready to jump you.
- 去拿枪，柯林 - 好的，爸
-Get my gun, Colin. -All right, Pa.
慢慢地靠近，陌生人
Just come in slow and easy, stranger.
把双手放在我们看得到的地方
And keep your hands where we can see 'em.
我叫奈勒斯罗林
Name's Linus Rawlings.
我肚子饿坏了 我绝无恶意
I'm hungrier than sin and real peaceful like.
- 你船上是什么东西？ - 海狸皮毛
-What've you got in the craft? -Beaver pelts.
我说过是海狸皮毛
I said beaver pelts.
我从没见过海狸皮毛 罗林先生
I never had a chance to see a beaver pelt, Mr. Rawlings.
那样的话，小姐 我拿一个给你看
Well, in that case, ma'am, I'll show you one.
你看
There you are.
好软喔
Oh, that's real soft.
这可是上等皮毛，小姐
It's a fine pelt, ma'am.
真对不起，先生
Now, my apologies, sir.
- 我们原先还担心你是海盗
We was afraid you might be a pirate.
我才不是海盗
I ain't no pirate.
来吧，咱们一起吃晚饭 多认识认识
Come on, let's have supper and get acquainted.
不用了，送你 你留着，小姐
No, no. That's yours. You keep that.
你动作还真快
Well, you sure set your cap in a hurry.
他是不是你一直在等的 砍柴樵夫呢？
Is he the backwoodsman you've been waiting for?
我看他八成有个老婆和六个孩子 在家里等着他呢
More than likely he's got a wife and six kids waiting for him.
"When I was single
"Went dressed up so fine
"Now I am married
"Go ragged all the time."
谢谢你，小姐 真的太好吃了
Thank you, ma'am, that was right tasty.
你才吃四盘 我一开始还以为你不喜欢吃呢
You've only ate four plates. I was beginning to think you didn't like it.
空腹一开始吃不了太多，小姐
Well, it don't pay to eat too much on an empty stomach, ma'am.
你为什么这么晚还在旅行？
How come you to be travelin' so late at night?
因为我很想赶快去匹兹堡
Well, I'm kinda anxious to get to Pittsburgh.
我已经很久没见到大城市 我想赶路快点到达
I ain't seen a city for a long time. I aim to whoop it up a little.
我们从未见过山中居民
We've never seen a mountain man before.
告诉我，洛矶山脉真有人家说的 那么高吗？
Tell me, them Rocky Mountains as high as they say?
这个…我也不是很清楚 我从来没爬上去过，我…
Well, now, I just don't rightly know. I never climbed one.
不过呢…那也不尽然啦…
I've, well...that just ain't exactly true.
吉姆布里哲和我…我们一开始先爬
Jim Bridger and me, we started up one of them little biddy...
洛矶山脚下的一座小山
...Rocky Mountain foothills, you know.
结果有一天 我们遇到一个人…
And then, one day, we see this fella...
他有一对巨大的白色翅膀…
...and he has a great big pair of white wings...
手里还抱着竖琴
...and a harp in his hand.
我便对吉姆说…
And I said to Jim...
“吉姆，我不喜欢这个人 看我们的样子”
...I said, "Jim, I don't like the way that fella's lookin' at us."
然后吉姆说他也不是很喜欢…
And Jim said he didn't care too much for it either...
结果我们便赶紧溜下山离开了
...so we both skidaddled down out of there...
直到今天 我从来没好好看过洛矶山一眼
...and to this day I ain't never had a good look at the Rocky Mountains.
- 我记得有一次… - 齐伯伦
-I remember one time-- -Zebulon.
- 怎样？
What?
一次一个人吹牛已经够了
One liar at a time is enough.
现在差不多该睡觉了
Well, then, I reckon it's about bedtime.
明天还得早起赶路呢
Gotta get an early start in the mornin'.
我们一起吃早餐，罗林先生
We'll be expectin' you for breakfast.
喔，你真是太客气了 普莱斯考特先生
Well, that's mighty hospitable, Mr. Prescott...
我经常一醒过来就要马上赶路
...but sometimes I wake up and get the urge to move.
日出之前我大概早就出发了 多谢你的邀请
I might be long gone by sunup, but I want to thank you.
- 非常感谢各位，晚安
I want to thank all of you. Good night.
- 晚安
Good night.
- 这些山中居民可真不寻常
Strange fellas, these mountain men.
- 是啊，来去有如一阵烟
Yeah, kind of like a wisp of smoke.
- 哇！那看起来好像我的毯子
By golly, that looks like my blanket.
- 是你的毯子没错
It is.
那我可就糊涂了，小姐 这床是给谁睡的呢？
Well, then, I'm a might confused, ma'am. Whose bed would it be?
给你睡的
Yours.
打从我离开东岸之后 再也没看过这样的床
I ain't never saw a bed like that since last time I come East.
你为什么要帮我？
Why'd you do it?
问一个女孩为什么帮一个男人做事 是不礼貌的
It ain't polite to ask a girl why she done something for a man.
是啊，我的言行的确有些失礼
No. Well, I reckon my manners ain't much at that.
不过，我倒是很感谢你 晚安，小姐
Anyway, I sure thank you. Good night, ma'am.
那些印地安女孩漂亮吗？
Are them Indian girls pretty?
我认为这得视男人到底有多久…
Well, now, I reckon that all depends on just how long a man's gone...
没看到女人而定
...without seein' one.
你有多久没看到白人女孩？
How long's it been since you seen a white girl?
我不确定你为什么这么问
I ain't quite sure why you asked that.
你觉得我有多漂亮？
How pretty do I look to you?
小姐…
你这样不会太开放了吧？
Ain't you just bein' a little bit forward?
你往上游走 我要往下游走
You're headed upriver and I'm headed down.
没有太多时间可以听你的回答
There's no time to get these questions answered.
你确定你想听我的回答？
You dead sure you want 'em answered?
是的
Yes.
老天…
Oh, glory be!
小姐，你好像从前曾经亲吻过
Ma'am, it seems like you've been kissed before.
我从未永久性地被亲吻过
I've never been kissed permanent before.
哇，你用字遣词真特别
By golly, you sure use surprising words.
我从没听过有人把“永久性”和 吻这玩意摆在一起形容
I never heard permanent mixed up with a thing like a kiss before.
我仍能感受到那份吻
I can still feel that kiss.
- 你能吗？
Can you?
- 你刚才讲了一句话…我还没忘记…
You said somethin' before we hadn't oughta forget:
我要往上游走 你要往下游走
I'm headin' upstream and you're headed downstream.
曾经分离过的情人终将再度聚首 - 小姐 - 叫我伊芙
Lovers have parted before and come together again.
伊芙，我是个罪孽深重的人
Eve, I, I'm a sinful man.
一个万劫不复的罪人
I'm deep, dark, sinful.
我正要前往匹兹堡再度当个罪人
I'm on my way to Pittsburgh to be sinful again.
我有可能会酒醉一个月
Likely I'll stay drunk for a month.
我将不会记得我泡过的女人…
I won't even remember the fancy gals I dally with...
或出自意气用事打过架的男人…
...or the men I carve up just out of pure cussedness...
更别说是记得你这个人
...any more than I'll remember you.
奈勒斯，我问你 你是否仍感觉到刚才那个吻？
Linus, I'm askin' you. Can you still feel that kiss?
伊芙…
Eve....
伊芙，你让我感觉好像 踮着脚站在一道窄路上…
Eve, you make me feel like a man standing on a narrow ledge...
迎面挑战一头恶狠狠的大熊
...comin' face to face with a grizzly bear.
我根本无法不去面对那处境
There just ain't no ignorin' the situation.
伊芙！
Eve!
- 伊芙！她人呢？ - 齐伯，怎么回事？
Eve! Where is she?
你在就好 我以为你和他走了
Anyways, you're here. I thought you'd gone with him.
- 走了？ - 是的，走了
-Gone? -Yes, gone.
我就知道你喜欢他…
I knowed you were settin' with him...
但我一直告诉自己 “至少她喜欢男人”
...but I kept tellin' myself at least she's lookin' at a man.
即便像那种一阵烟的男人也好
Even a wisp of smoke like that is better than--
你在哭？为他哭？ 这是什么意思？
Are you cryin'? Cryin' for him? Now, what does that mean?
告诉我这是什么意思？
Now, tell me what that means.
没什么意思，爸
Nothin', Pa.
你几点上床睡觉的？
What time did you come to bed?
很早就睡了，爸
It was early, Pa.
不…很晚
It wasn't. It was late.
女儿啊，我只问你一次…
Daughter, I'm only gonna ask you once.
有没有任何事情是值得 你妈和我担心的？
Is there anything for your ma and pa to worry about?
没有，爸，没事
No, Pa, there ain't.
他会再回来的
He'll be back.
我会再见到他的
I'll see him again.
但你原本以为今天早上会见到他 你是这么想的
But you expected to see him this morning. You know you did.
我不管，我会再见到他的
I don't care. I'll see him again.
你看…
Look.
- 你让一个大男人为你这么做？
You got a growed man to do that?
- 没错，就像书里写的一样
I did, just like in the book.
你有让他对你说那些疯狂的话吗？
Did you get him to say them crazy words?
我说过了，重点不在那些话 而是那种感觉
I told you before, it ain't the words, it's the sentiment.
你是说他没有笑那些无聊的事？
You mean he didn't even giggle or nothin' at such foolishness?
他说那是很严肃的一件事
He said it was a real solemn occasion...
好像在急流中不用划板一样
...like shootin' the rapids without a paddle.
不管他怎么说，他这么做只是为了 打发你好赶紧脱身
No matter what he said, he did it just to get rid of you so as he could clear out.
你知道是这样没错的
You know that's so.
算你走运他那么做 你真打算懵懵懂懂过一辈子？
And you're lucky he did. Do you want to live like a squaw all your life?
随便你想说什么都行
Go on, say anything you like...
我一定会再见到他的 我知道我会的
...but I'll see him again. I know I will.
而且他才没有老婆 也没有六个孩子
And he ain't got a wife and six kids.
他还没讨老婆呢！
He ain't got a wife at all yet.
（贩卖酒品 杰布霍金斯）
嘿，皮耶！有人从上游来了
Pierre, someone's comin' upriver.
有客人来了！
Customer.
好像是捕兽皮者  瞧那鼓鼓的一团？
Trapper, seems like. See how that cover bellies up?
有可能是皮毛
Could be furs.
口渴吗，先生？
Thirsty, mister?
比热锅上的蚱蜢还要渴
Drier than a grasshopper on a hot griddle.
那么，欢迎您光临我们的小旅舍
Well, welcome to our little inn, sir.
我叫杰布霍金斯 曾经是阿拉巴马州的国民军上校
My name is Jeb Hawkins, late colonel of the Alabama militia.
- 你要去哪？ - 匹兹堡
-Where you bound for? -Pittsburgh.
匹兹堡？
Pittsburgh?
他好像有一整船的皮毛呢，爸
Looks like he's got a whole canoe of furs, Pop.
- 一定是个山中居民 - 没错
-A sure enough mountain man. -Indeed.
咱们的探险家开疆辟土前进到 遥远的太平洋海岸
One of our brave explorers gonna extend our domain to the far shores of the Pacific.
一定要请你喝最上等的酒 威士忌？
Nothin' but the finest for you, sir. Whiskey?
- 好的
Right.
- 这里面没加胡椒或响尾蛇
No pepper or rattlesnake heads in this.
除了甜美的麦芽啥都没乱加
Nothin' but the pure grain and the sweet kiss of the malt.
- 不必用杯子，我直接整罐喝了
Never mind the cup, I'll just take the jug.
- 喔，真正的山中居民
A real mountain man, eh?
- 你为国旗敬一杯吧！
I trust you'll toast our noble banner, sir.
- 那当然
I sure will.
你说得没错 这果然是上等好酒
Golly, you're right. That's real sippin' liquor.
爸，既然他是捕兽皮者
Pa, him being a trapper...
你想他会知道我们抓到的是什么野兽？
...do you suppose he might know what that varmint is we got?
或许吧…我想他应该会晓得
Well, say, now, he might. Yes, sir, he just might.
我们抓到一只穴居野兽…
Sir, we catched us a cave-dwellin' critter...
在我们从没去过的地方抓到的
...that no man in these parts has ever seen before.
如果你能告诉我们 那到底是什么玩意就太好了
And, you know, it'd be right satisfyin' havin' you tell us what it is.
我对穴居野兽不太了解
Well, I don't know too much about cave-dwellin' varmints.
就在这附近 把你的酒带着
Just yonder, take your jug.
这个…我… 我不知道…
I don't know....
就在这里
It's right over here.
你在匹兹堡有没有女朋友？
You know any sweet-talkin' girls in Pittsburgh?
没有…一个都没有…还没
No, nary a one, yet.
我和爸正考虑去那里度假呢
Pop and I are hopin' we'll vacation there.
我会在《杜肯酒店》 如果还没被烧掉的话
I'll be at the Duquesne House if it ain't burned down.
嘿…
Hey there, now....
小美女… 你确定你的野兽关在这里？
You pretty girl, you sure you got a varmint in here?
你有听到吗？
Do you hear him?
它的呼吸声又大又猛
He breathes loud and fierce.
- 我们把它关在那边的洞里 - 你们把它关在这里？
-We keep him in this hole just yonder. -You keep him in there?
你得再靠近点看
You gotta look a little closer.
他看到野兽了，爸
Well, he seed the varmint, Pa.
- 干得好 女儿
Well done, daughter.
- 我不太确定…
I ain't so sure.
他的肌肉结实 我可以感觉到他的肋骨锐利如刀片
He was hard-muscled. I could feel the blade just kinda skitter along his ribs.
喔，你只需要多练习几次 没什么
You just need more practice, that's all.
真可惜你没有你妈的绝招
It's a pity you ain't got the knack your ma had...
祝她安息
...Lord rest her soul.
好吧，各位，快行动吧
All right, men....
快点！快点！
Lay into it, men.
咱们去大赚一票！
Come on, we've got a lot of fish to fry.
到岛上去！
Down to the island.
通知爸爸拓荒者的船来了
Tell Pa them settlers' rafts are comin'.
（贝罗商店 供需品及以货易货）
（贝罗商店 还缺什么吗？）
（匹兹堡价钱）
我可以买这瓶香水吗，爸？
Can't I have this toilet water, Pa?
- 是原装巴黎香水呢 - 多少钱？
-Genuine Parisian Accent, it says. -How much is it?
只要一毛五
It's only 15 cents.
一毛五？给我放回去
Fifteen cents! Put it back.
是啊，没错 省几毛钱，几块钱便因运而生
You're right, sir. Absolutely right. You save the pennies and dollars will grow.
钱慢慢积少成多
Likely you've growed many a dollar, ain't you?
贝罗先生，我这一生总避免自己成为 百万富翁
Mr. Peddler, all my life I've been strivin' to avoid becomin' a millionaire...
我目前为止还挺成功的
...and I think I've succeeded right well.
我袜子里只有几块钱 我不会乱花的
I've got a little put away in the sock and it'll stay right there.
我完全赞同你的说法
Well, now, them's my sentiments exactly.
先生，你看起来倒像个有钱人
Now, you, sir-- You look like a man of property.
若要我猜的话 我想你身价差不多一千元
Now, if I was to bet, I'd say you was worth a $1,000.
- 是不是挺接近呢？
Pretty close to the mark?
- 差不多，或许吧
Well, close, maybe.
- 柯林，我们还剩下多少火药？
Colin, how much powder we got left?
- 别害怕，别怕
Don't be afeerd, now, don't be afeerd.
这里有女人和小孩
Now, there's women and children here.
你们不会希望我们开枪扫射吧？
You gents wouldn't want us to have to start shootin', now, would you?
大家冷静点
Be of good cheer, folks.
咱们的使命是开疆辟土…
Why, it's in our noble tradition to conquer the wilderness...
凭着我们的赤手空拳和果断的心
...with nothin' but our bare hands and stout hearts.
你们大家可以拿出祖先的克难精神 再建造新的船筏
You can build new rafts and sally forth in the spirit of your forefathers.
你这个不要脸的小人！
Why, you pious old scoundrel.
你会下地狱！
I'll see you burn.
美国人不是那么好欺负的！
Americans can't be whipped.
是他！
It's him.
我就知道他会回来！是他！
I knew he'd come back. It's him.
让我们一起来祈祷
Now, let us pray.
上帝啊…
Oh, Lord...
感谢您让我们逃过一劫
...we thank Thee for our salvation.
我们希望将死者的灵魂交托给您
We commit the souls of our dead to Thy gentle keepin'.
祈祷我们之中受伤的人能早日康复
We pray for a speedy recovery of our wounded.
另外还有一件事…
And, now, another matter.
上帝啊…
Oh, Lord...
在未曾请教过您的情况下…
...without consulting with Thee...
我们将几个被魔鬼缠附的灵魂 送到您那里
...we have sent Thy way some souls whose evil ways passeth all understanding.
我们恳求您收容那些灵魂
We ask Thee humbly to receive them...
不管您愿不愿意接受
...whether You want 'em or not.
阿们
Amen.
这得花点功夫修补
It'll be a job.
我一定能把它修好 然后前去匹兹堡
But I guess I can patch her up good enough to get to Pittsburgh.
- 奈勒斯… - 别这样，伊芙…
-Linus. -Now, Eve...
我们别再谈这件事了
...let's just not talk any more about it.
奈勒斯，我告诉你 你根本不懂你自己的心
Linus, I'm tellin' you, you don't know your own mind.
或许是，或许不是
Maybe so, maybe not.
我并不是说我没偶尔想起你
I know I ain't sayin' that you haven't been on my mind some.
我并没那样说
I ain't sayin' that.
但我仍和那个海盗女 一起跑去看野兽
But I still went to see the varmint with that pirate girl.
我永远都会想要跑去看“野兽”，伊芙
I'll always be goin' to see the varmint, Eve.
我根本不是农夫或丈夫的料
I, I just ain't cut out to be a farmer or a husband.
奈勒斯，我再也不会提起这件事…
Linus, I ain't never bringing up the subject again...
不管我会不会再见到你
...whether ever I see you or not.
这对我们大家都好
Now, it's for the best.
我希望你一切顺心，伊芙
I wish you Godspeed, Eve.
我已经很久没对人那样说了
And I ain't said that to anybody for a long time.
我看到前面有急流，爸 白花花的浪头
I can see rapids ahead, Pa. White water.
你们看！
Look. Look.
喔，我们一定走错叉路了
Oh, we must've taken the wrong fork.
把船停靠岸！
Let's beach her on this side.
哈维！
Harvey!
急流！
Rapids.
前面有急流！把船靠岸！
Rapids ahead! Beach her!
把船靠岸！
Beach her!
稳住船身！
Hold her steady.
拉住！
Strain!
爸，我们被卷进急流了！
Pa, we're in the current.
进去里面，齐克
Get inside, Zeke.
不！我不要！
No, I don't wanna.
往直行，爸！
Straighten her, Pa.
莉莉丝！
Lilith!
稳住！
Hold it steady!
没办法！
I can't!
快去！快去帮爸爸！
Go on. Go on and help Pa.
我来！
I'll get it.
莉莉丝！莉莉丝！
Lilith! Lilith!
趴下！
Lie down!
怎么回事？
What happened?
他们走错河道 往瀑布冲下去了
They took the wrong fork of the river and they went over the falls.
你可知道是哪个人家？
Did you happen to hear the name of the family?
普莱斯考特家族，好像是他们
Prescott, I think. Something like that.
一旦好好安葬过他们…
As soon as they're buried decent...
我就要搭上第一艘回东部的船！
...l'm heading back East on the first boat that comes along.
你若头脑清楚的话 你也会这么做
And if you were in your right mind, you would, too.
喔，奈勒斯…
Oh, Linus.
摇滚年代，离我远去
"Rock of ages, cleft for me
让我把自己你放在心里
"Let me hide myself in thee
让泪水和流血
"Let the water and the blood
从此远离
"From thy side, a healing flood
双重医治我的罪过
"Be of sin the double cure
把我的罪恶洗净
"Cleanse me from its guilt and power."
你陪我散步一下好吗，伊芙？
Would you walk with me a piece, Eve?
伊芙，我…
Eve, I....
伊芙，我刚才一路划过来时 我心里想着…
Eve, all the time I was paddlin' down here I was thinkin'...
如果我看到你还活着 我就…
...if I found you alive, I'd--
你愿意和我一起去匹兹堡吗，伊芙？
Would you come to Pittsburgh with me, Eve?
喔，奈勒斯… 我要留在这里
I'm stayin' right here.
不管怎样我都不会离开这里一步
I ain't movin' a foot one way or the other.
能告诉我为什么吗？
Now would you explain that a little?
爸爸妈妈想到西部开辟一座农场…
Ma and Pa, they wanted a farm in the West...
他们只走到这么远
...and this is as far as they got.
我觉得这是上帝要农场搭盖的地方
Seems to me this is where the Lord wanted the farm to be.
可是你的弟弟山姆受伤那么严重 冬天就要来了…
But your brother, Sam, he's bad hurt, and winter's comin'--
再怎么说都没用 我非这么做不可
There's no sense talkin' about it. I'm gonna do it.
伊芙，你这样根本不合理啊
Eve, you just ain't makin' much sense.
我想有半数前来西部的人 都不是按牌理出牌的
Half the people that come West don't make much sense, I reckon.
好吧
All right.
老天，你真是个意志坚定的女人
By golly, you're a strong-minded woman.
我向你保证 那是我最后一次看野兽了
I reckon I seen that varmint for the last time.
迈向西部之路并不比 追求真爱来得平顺
The westward course was no smoother than that of true love.
不仅得面对残酷大自然的考验 另外还有战争的阻碍
Not only the hard hand of nature was against it, but the impediment of war.
美墨边境地带一直不断出现战事
Trouble over land smoldered along the Mexican border.
并不是所有美国人都赞成战争 包括伊利诺州的众议员亚柏林肯
Not all Americans were for war, including Congressman Abe Lincoln of Illinois.
但战事仍爆发了 到最后…
But a war did break out...
许多带着浓厚西班牙色彩地名的新领地
...and in the end vast new territories came into the Union...
被纳入联邦政府的一部分…
...along with their rich Spanish names:
里欧格蓝德…圣塔菲… 亚柏考基…艾尔帕索
Rio Grande, Santa Fe, Albuquerque, El Paso...
还有其中最出名的是…加州
...and most glittering of all, California...
以一本十五世纪小说里 一处充满珍珠与黄金神秘小岛为命名的
...named after a mythical island of pearls and gold in a 15th century novel.
而现在1848年…
Here, in 1848...
在萨特磨坊 有个人无意间在沟底处…
...at Sutter's Mill, a man found something he wasn't even looking for...
发现了一样东西
...at the bottom of a ditch.
他发现这个东西的消息传遍各地…
And the cry of his discovery was heard clear across the continent...
波士顿…纽约…莎凡那…甚至横越大洋
...in Boston, New York, Savannah, and across the oceans...
至伦敦…巴黎…柏林
...in London, Paris, Berlin.
然而这场黄金热最疯狂的地点
But nowhere was the clamor of gold...
就是在圣路易斯市…
...heard more eagerly than in St. Louis...
该地是全世界最忙碌的皮毛交易中心
...the busiest fur trading center in the world...
是纽约以西最喧嚣，最态意妄为 最骄气的城市
...and the noisiest, bawdiest, most uppity town west of New York.
（明星歌舞团）
（登台演唱者：莉莉普莱斯考特）
"Boys, hold your hosses
"We're still the bosses
"Please hold your hosses
"Till we get...
"...to the dance! "
我说不超过三号
I say there's no more than three.
- 六号 - 六号？
Six? It's all that lace that fooled you. I still say three.
是那些蕾丝的关系 我说是三号
克里夫可是女人衬裙专家
Watch him. I hear Cleve's an expert on petticoats.
反正你永远没办法证实
Anyway, you can never prove it.
咱们扑克牌局要迟到了
Gentlemen, we're going to be late for that poker game.
我刚让你花了那么多钱 吃晚餐…
I've just stuck you for the most expensive dinner in St. Louis...
我还想再捞你一笔 我赌一百元那件衬裙不超过六号
...and I don't mind sticking you a little bit deeper.
我赌一百元那件衬裙不超过六号
I'll lay you $100 if it's no less than six.
- 你要如何证实？ - 到后台去查啊
-How will you prove it? -Go backstage and find out.
- 我和你一起去
If I go back and check with you.
- 可以
Fair enough.
第二个女孩
Second girl.
- 普莱斯考特小姐？普莱斯考特小姐？ - 等一下
-Miss Prescott? -Later.
这事挺重要的
It's rather important.
每次都说很重要
It's always important.
愈老的家伙事情愈重要
The older they are, the more important it gets.
普莱斯考特小姐 我是海蓝席贝瑞…
Miss Prescott, please. I'm Hylan Seabury...
强纳森布鲁克斯的律师
...attorney in the matter of Jonathan Brooks.
你不知道他是谁？
He means nothing to you?
那糟老头？
That old goat?
那你一定对他具有某种意义 普莱斯考特小姐
You must've meant something to him, Miss Prescott.
- 为什么？ - 他的遗嘱里有提到你
-Why? -You're included in his will.
当然，你得亲自去加州取得这份遗产
Of course, you'll have to make the trip to California to claim the bequest.
我才不要去加州
Well, now, I wouldn't go to California...
就算约翰亚斯特把整个旧金山留给我
...if John Jacob Astor left me San Francisco.
我想亚斯特先生在那里并没有财产
I don't think Mr. Astor had holdings there.
无论如何，布鲁克斯先生物产的收入 可是不容轻忽的
However, the yield from Mr. Brooks' property is not to be scorned.
- 什么收入？
Yield of what?
- 黄金，普莱斯考特小姐，黄金
Gold, Miss Prescott. Gold.
- 黄金？ - 正是
-Gold? -Precisely.
你拥有一座金矿，普莱斯考特小姐
You own a gold mine, Miss Prescott.
首周便收入三千五百元
It yielded $3,500 the very first week.
金矿？
Gold mine?
这个…我… 那个可爱的糟老头
That sweet old goat!
老天…
呃…
真是意想不到的惊喜
This is an unexpected pleasure.
- 钱呢？ - 钱？
Where's the money?
钱？
Money?
喔，对了…你指的是 我们之前的小小协议
Oh, yes. You're referring, of course, to our little agreement.
先拿出一百元吧…
One hundred to start you off...
另外还有我赢钱的部分
...and my share of the winnings.
真不好意思…那一百元已经没有了
Well, I'm somewhat embarrassed to report that the $100 no longer exists.
那一百元…我可以向你保证…
That $100, I assure you...
将是你有史以来做过最棒的投资
...will turn out to be the best investment you have ever made.
我有几个计昼，各位
I have plans, gentlemen...
是你们从未想过的计昼
...beyond your wildest dreams.
我要替你们赢来一座金矿的股份
I'm gonna earn you a piece of a gold mine.
金矿
Gold mine!
你才不可能会赚到什么钱
You ain't gonna earn nothin'!
你永远都不成气候 做不了任何事…
You ain't gonna be nothin', you ain't gonna do nothin'...
除非你在明早之前 给我们一百元！
...unless we get that $100 back by the morning.
格兰姆斯，你这话不是认真的吧
Grimes, you don't mean that.
- 你可别干掉会下金蛋的鹅
You're gonna kill off the golden goose.
- 随便你怎么讲，先生
Call it what you want, mister.
我们会等着收钱的
We'll be waitin'.
（加州一奥勒冈 篷车队）
密苏里州的独立市是 移民者通往各地的起点
Independence, Missouri, was the jump-off point for emigrants from everywhere.
脚踏实地，敬畏上帝 前往奥勒冈的务农人家…
Solid, God-fearing families bound for the farmlands of Oregon...
以及前往加州淘金 梦想一夜致富的冒险者
...and get-rich-quick adventurers raced for the gold of California.
试试看
Try it.
- 你有篷车吧？
You got a wagon, I suppose?
- 我可以买一辆
I can get one.
有人帮你拉？
And a team to pull it?
我需要的一切都有了
I can get everything I need.
- 你有丈夫吗？
You got a husband?
- 我单身，摩根先生
I'm single, Mr. Morgan.
没有旅伴？
No travelin' companion?
- 没，我一个人
No, I'm travelin' alone.
- 我的篷车队可不行这样
Not on my wagon train.
单身女人会引来男人妄想
Alone and single brings out the deviltry in a man.
把他们弄得六神无主 他们已经够狂野了
Gets 'em all worked up and they're wild enough already.
我不打算和别人打交道，摩根先生
I intend to keep to myself, Mr. Morgan.
喔，像你这种女人？
A woman of your sort?
有一天你会发现自己惹了麻烦 才苦恼不晓得到底要找谁算帐
One day you'd find yourself in trouble and there'd be hell to pay just figurin' out who.
你说什么，摩根先生？
What did you say, Mr. Morgan?
你这女人个性挺泼辣的嘛 我喜欢个性强的女人
Well, now, ain't you the feisty one! I like spirit in a woman.
你这张藏在妆底下的脸 还挺好看的
You got a pretty face under that powder, too.
在这层衣服底下 应是一副美好结实的身子，我想
And a fine, sturdy body under them clothes, I wager.
有个女人姓克雷格 艾姬克雷格
There's a woman named Clegg, Aggie Clegg.
你去找她吧
Why don't you go see her?
谢谢
Thanks.
我告诉你了，不要！
I told you, no.
我打算在这场旅途上找个丈夫
I was hoping to make this trip with a husband.
上周差点找到一个
Nearly got one last week.
我听说在加州每四十个男人 只有一个女人
Look, I hear there's 40 men to every woman in California.
- 克雷格小姐，我愿意付你钱 - 我不需要钱
Miss Clegg, I'd be willing to pay you.
我需要的是男人
I don't need money, I need a man.
任何男人都行
Any man.
早安，女士们
Mornin', ladies.
今早天气真好
Beautiful mornin'.
请问你是不是 莉莉普莱斯考特小姐？
Would you, by any chance, happen to be Miss Lily Prescott?
除非你脑子搞不清楚
Not unless you got a big imagination.
那一定就是你罗
Then, you must be the lady in question.
克里夫凡伟伦，普莱斯考特小姐 听从你吩咐
Cleve van Valen, Miss Prescott, at your service.
从这里到加州 敝人听从你差遣
At your every command from here to California.
谢谢你
Well, thank you, but whatever you're offering, I don't need.
不过，你提供的任何服务 我都不需要
或许你不了解…
Perhaps you don't understand.
是的，我了解 对于识别骗子我特别在行
Yes, I do. I know a tinhorn when I see one.
普莱斯考特小姐…
Miss Prescott!
我是真心想替你做事 做一份事，拿一分钱
I'm offerin' you an honest days' work for an honest days' pay.
再见，凡伟伦先生 再见
Goodbye, Mr. van Valen. Goodbye.
很荣幸认识你，克雷格小姐
Well, it's been a pleasure to meet you, Miss Clegg.
请容我说，我从未过过女人 拥有一头如此美丽的秀发
May I say I have never seen a woman with more beautiful hair.
我想那头发如果挂在…
What a prize catch it will make...
印地安人腰上一定很好看
...hanging from the waist of an Indian.
如此美女独自在荒野里
Beauty, alone in the wilderness...
谁来保护你呢？
...and who's to protect you?
没人
No one.
每个人都自顾不暇了
Not one person won't be looking after himself.
好吧…
Well....
日安，女士们
Good day, ladies.
…日安
Good day.
从来都没有人那样对我说过
Nobody ever said that to me before.
说什么？
What?
说我有一头美丽的秀发
That I had such...such beautiful hair.
你知道吗？
You know something?
我感觉你可以吸引来许多男人
I got a hunch you're gonna draw men like fish to the bait.
或许我可以顺便挑中一个
Maybe I can catch one of them while they swim by.
我愿意当你的伙伴
You got yourself a partner.
谢谢你
Thank you.
怎么样？
How's it, Ben?
从这里一切净空 下一段路小心一个小泥坑就是了
It's all clear up through here. Look for a little mudhole up through the next pocket.
- 有多远？ - 喔，大约八分之一哩路吧
-How far? -Maybe half or a quarter.
- 好的，谢谢 - 在那山脊上可登高望远
-Well, thanks. -Looks a little higher up on that ridge.
上面有个水洞 差不多半哩，咱们往那里去
There's a water hole up there about half a mile. Let's head for it.
前面半哩处有个水洞
Water hole about a half a mile ahead.
嘿，你在拉车
Hey, you're drivin'.
我是在农场里长大的
I was raised on a farm.
前面半哩处有个水洞
Water hole about a half a mile ahead.
嘿，艾姬？
Hey, Aggie....
- 这个你要吗？ - 当然
Can you use these?
谢谢
Yeah, sure. Thanks.
女士们
Ladies.
听从你吩咐
At your service.
我以为已经把你给甩了
I thought we'd gotten rid of you.
我无法想像你们俩独自上路 没有我从旁相助
Well, I just couldn't bear to think of you two makin' this trip without my help.
我若听到你有个三长两短
If I was to hear later on that somethin' happened to you...
我一定不会原谅我自己的
...l'd never forgive myself.
你一个人跑一百哩？
You came 100 miles alone?
我没计算路程，摩根先生 不过你说了就算
Well, I had no way of countin' the miles, Mr. Morgan, but I'll take your word for it.
那你得再跑个一百哩，先生 往回走
You've got another 100, mister. Goin' back.
我说过，当篷车坏掉时 我要懂得修车的人…
I told ya, when a wagon breaks down, I want men who can fix it...
不是赌车子能撑多久的人
...not bet how long it'll take.
你不会想就这样把我赶跑吧？
You don't mean you'll turn me out?
让我沦落入野蛮印地安人手中？
Pass me adrift at the mercy of savage Indians?
如果你再不走 我就把你…
If you don't get movin', I'll cast you adrift--
我知道你想要讲什么，先生
I appeal to your sportin' instinct, sir.
我要和你打赌 我将留在这车队里
I'm prepared to wager you that I stay with this train.
- 你要赌，来啊！
Well, you got a wager.
- 等一下！等一下！
Wait a minute.
是这样的，我雇请了这个人
The fact is, I hired this man.
我们愿意替他作保
We'll put up his stake.
是这样吗，普莱斯考特小姐？
Is that right, Miss Prescott?
克雷格小姐说了算数
If Miss Clegg says so.
小姐…
Ma'am...
我将毕生感激不尽
...l'll be forever grateful.
我这就去卸下我的行李
Now, I'll unpack my gear.
艾姬莎，你疯啦？
Agatha, have you gone crazy?
他说他想老老实实做事
He says he's a man wantin' to do an honest days work.
他可以的，我跟你保证
And he'll do it. I can promise you that.
最后一台篷车 快点跟上
Hey, you men on that last wagon, keep up that slack.
快点跟上
Keep it up.
大家往前走，继续往前走！
Get that team movin'. Keep 'em movin' there.
别让绳索垂下去！
Don't let those lines sag.
跟上队伍！跟上队伍！
Keep 'em up. Keep 'em up.
大家继续往前进！
Keep those teams movin'.
继续往前进！
Keep 'em movin'.
别让绳索垂下去！
Don't let those lines sag.
队伍中间的人 继续往前进！
You on that middle team, keep 'em movin'.
- 进去！ - 在这里，爸
Get in there.
进去！
进去！进去！骡子！
Get in there, mule.
我受到如此多关心真的很感动 普莱斯考特小姐
I'm just overwhelmed by all this attention, Miss Prescott.
我要向你坦白…
I want to confess...
关于替你工作的事 我对你们撒谎
...I have lied about why I wanted to work for you.
我知道
I know.
真正的原因是 我爱上了你
The real reason is, of course, that I'm in love with you.
先别说话…， 那是实话
Now, it's the truth.
打从我第一眼看到你
From the first moment I saw you...
我就知道我不能没有你
...l've known that I couldn't live without you.
我可不想害你活不成，凡伟伦先生
I'd hate to be the cause of your death, Mr. van Valen.
我这话可不是随便说说 普莱斯考特小姐
I don't speak lightly, Miss Prescott.
我已准备好当个负责任且忠实的好丈夫
I'm prepared to assume the responsibilities of a faithful husband.
喔，那你是否已准备承担责任…
Oh, and are you ready to assume the responsibilities...
掌管我的财产呢，凡伟伦先生？
...of my property, too, Mr. van Valen?
真的？什么样的财产？
Really? What, what kind of property?
黄金，凡伟伦先生
Gold, Mr. van Valen.
就我所知，有上吨的黄金
Gold by the ton from what I understand.
闪亮，澄黄，耀眼的黄金
Bright, yellow, shiny gold.
哇！我不晓得呢
I had no idea.
- 我想也是
I'm sure you hadn't.
- 普莱斯考特小姐，我真的是…
Miss Prescott, I really mean--
艾姬莎来了
Here comes Agatha.
如果你必须向人求婚…
If you must propose to somebody...
我建议你向她下跪求婚
...I suggest you get on your knees to her.
更何况，她有一头美丽的秀发
Besides, she has beautiful hair.
瞧瞧他们…
Look at 'em.
他们好像准备要埋葬死人一样
You'd think they was gettin' ready to bury somebody.
难道咱们还不够苦闷吗？
Ain't we worn down enough as it is?
那咱们来激发点士气
Well, let's wake 'em up.
听着，各位…
Listen, everybody.
来吧，每个人都来
"Come on along, everybody come along
这里有明亮的月亮和星光
"While that moon am shinin' bright
来吧，放开你的嗓门一起歌唱
"Come on along And raise your voice in song
今天晚我们要骚动起来
"We're gonna raise a ruckus tonight
我们没时间坐着，一起骚动起来
"It ain't no time to sit 'n brood Raise a ruckus tonight
调动你的热情一起骚动起来
"It's time to strike a lively mood Raise a ruckus tonight
雷兹，去把你的班卓琴弹起来让大家热情骚动起来
"Go and get that old banjo Raise a ruckus tonight
只需要拍着节奏让你的脚和身体骚动起来
"Just pat your foot and tap your toe Raise a ruckus tonight
你听到了我说的吗？来吧，孩子们，来吧
"Do ya hear me? Come on along, little children, come along
这里有明亮的月亮和星光
"While that moon am shinin' bright
过来，把这把洗衣板当琴弦弹
"Come along now and tune up that string And let that banjo ring
今天晚我们要骚动起来
"We're gonna raise a ruckus tonight! "
现在唱出来吧！
Sing it out, now!
这样才对嘛！士气激昂！
That's the spirit. That's the way to feel.
喔，你好哇，摩根先生！
Oh, hiya, Mr. Morgan!
艾姬…午餐吃的
Aggie, for lunch.
谢谢，好一篓肥鱼
Thanks. Nice not to fish.
什么事，摩根先生？
What is it, Mr. Morgan?
普莱斯考特小姐，我一直在想…
Miss Prescott, I've been thinking.
你是我走遍各地 见过最美丽的女人
Wet or dry, you're the handsomest woman I ever did see.
个性活泼，身材健美
Spirit and a fine sturdy body.
绝佳组合，普莱斯考特小姐
It's a noble combination, Miss Prescott.
我想生孩子对你而言应该就像 滚木头一样简单
Why, for you, child-bearin' would come as easy as rolling off a log.
我还宁愿滚木头呢，摩根先生
Well, I think I'd rather roll off a log, Mr. Morgan.
小姐，我告诉你 你绝对是生孩子的料
Ma'am, I'm tellin' you, you got the build for it.
我要你当我的老婆
I want you for my wife.
我在麻塞德有一座牧牛农场
I've got a cattle ranch just below the Merced.
我将在那里安顿下来 衣食无缺
I'll be settlin' down there, fit and proper.
我相信你是很衣食无缺 摩根先生
I'm sure you're very fit and proper, Mr. Morgan.
那么…
Well, then...
你不可能嫁给比我更好的人
...you just couldn't do no better than marryin' me.
我们可以很快地组个美满家庭 生儿育女
Why, we'd have ourselves a fine family in no time at all.
我相信是可以的
I believe that.
我很抱歉，摩根先生…
I'm sorry, Mr. Morgan, but...
我无法接受你的求婚
...I can't accept your proposal.
为什么不？
Why not?
Well....
女人喜欢听点甜言蜜语的话
A woman likes to hear something a little more inviting.
那不就是我的意思？ 对你甜言蜜语
Well, ain't that what I've been doin'? Invitin' you?
请你和我分享我的人生 普莱斯考特小姐
Invitin' you to share my life, Miss Prescott.
很抱歉，摩根先生…
I'm sorry, Mr. Morgan.
是不是有别的事情？
It's somethin' else, ain't it?
一定有别的事情困扰着你
Must be somethin' else naggin' at you.
好吧… 我不会让它阻止我的 普莱斯考特小姐
I don't aim to let it stop me, Miss Prescott.
我向你保证
You can count on that.
他想要什么？
What did he want?
孩子
Children.
孩子？
Children?
真是的…
Well, I'll be--
他干嘛不找对的人呢？
Why didn't he come shopping at the right store?
- 我押这些 - 这个嘛…
I'll take a look.
咱们是玩小赌本吗？
Gentlemen, are we pikers?
我要再加筹码 还要再押这把好枪…
I'm gonna see and I'm gonna raise this fine pistol.
伦敦制，专门打熊用的枪
London-made and loaded for bear.
我也要参加一份
I'll take part of that bet.
我说过我绝不允许你搞这种勾当…
I told you I wouldn't stand for you fleecin' any--
夏安族
Cheyennes.
我们寡不敌众 必须赶紧逃跑
There's too many. We'll have to make a run for it.
用篷车根本跑不过他们
You can't outrun them with the wagons.
一开跑之后 整个队伍要散开
The minute you get movin' cut your lead teams loose.
- 你疯啦？ - 快点，动作快！
Have you gone crazy?
他们要的是我们的货 不是我们的人
Chances are they want our stock more than us.
你是赌徒没错吧？ 好了，咱们走吧
You're a gambler, ain't you? All right, let's get movin'.
大家凑紧一点！
Keep 'em closed up there.
我不知道该如何解开它们
I don't know how to unhook them.
克里夫，小心！
Cleve, watch out!
乔！载我一程！
Joe, pick me up.
天一破晓我们就出发
We'll be movin' at daybreak.
我带几个人去看能不能找到他
I'll take a few men and see if we can find him.
帮他好好做一场基督徒的葬礼仪式
Give him a decent, Christian burial.
有人来了！有人来了！
Someone's comin'! Someone's comin'!
这车子我可以租你一天一块钱 还可以派人手随同
I can let you have this rig for $1 a day and I'll give you a good team.
- 明天早上来取 - 好的
-Pick it up in the morning. -Fine.
请问布鲁克斯家往哪里走？
Could you tell me the way to the Brook's claim?
就在河边
Well, the claims are down by the river.
- 我该走哪条路？
Which road should I take?
- 只有一条路，沿着河走
Only one road, along the river.
- 谢谢 - 不客气
-Thank you. -Sure welcome.
我们要找赫金斯先生
We're looking for a Mr. Huggins.
我就是
You found him.
这位是莉莉丝普莱斯考特
This is Miss Lilith Prescott.
我想也是
I figured.
他们说你是个美人
They told me you was a real looker.
这片地都是你的了 正如布鲁克斯声明的
It's all here for you. Just the way Mr. Brooks staked it out.
从前大概有二十人在工作
Must have had 20 men workin' on it.
那现在人呢？ 是谁在挖黄金呢？
Where are they now? Who's digging the gold?
黄金？我和米莉来这里之前 从未见过如此上等货
Gold? I ain't never seen a better grade since I come here with Millie.
只有一点点
But just a pocket, though.
整个庞大工程却只挖到一点点
The whole shebang, nothin' but a pocket.
喔，我们总共赚了四千二百元
Oh, we cleared $4,200 before it played out.
关于那四千二百元…
Now, about that $4,200....
布鲁克斯先生在心脏病发作之前 化掉了三千元
Mr. Brooks, he spent three before his heart give out.
我花了六百元买一座铜棺材
I put up $600 for a brass-handled casket.
剩下的钱就算是 你欠我帮忙看管这地方
I figure the rest you owe me for sittin' on your claim.
小姐，这样才公平，是吧？
Oh, miss, I mean, that's only fair, ain't it?
你是不是这么认为…？
I mean, wouldn't you...?
好奇怪的一对
Funny pair, all right.
那你们呢？
How about you boys over here?
快来看全新的表演节目
Come and see the brand new attraction.
超级刺激，超级性感 请进吧，各位先生
It's exciting and sensational. Step right in, gentlemen.
"Are you wanted for life 'Cause you left your poor wife
"When she caught you sniffin' a cork, My friend
"Hey, what was your name in New York
"Oh, what was your name in the East
"And how recently was you released
"Are you ridin' the rails 'Cause you held up the mails
"Or was it the females you held, you beast
"Oh, what was your name in the East
"Oh, what was your name in the states
"Though you suffered the cruelest of fates
"Way out here in the West
"Everybody's a guest
"So line up and fill up your plates, My friend
"Whoever you was in the states! "
普莱斯考特小姐？
Miss Prescott.
哈罗，摩根先生
Hello, Mr. Morgan.
这里有点挤，不方便请你进来坐
I'd invite you in, but it's a little cramped.
像你这么好条件的女人 不应该过这种日子
This is no life for a fine woman like you.
我听说你的金矿没着落
I heard your mine was played out.
可是你那个爱玩的朋友呢？
But, where's your fancy friend?
克里夫？
Cleve?
听说他跑去汉镇了
The last I heard, he was in Hangtown.
你是说那个没出息的人 丢下你跑掉了？
You mean that no-good went off and left you?
他丢下我跑掉了
He went off and left me...
但我不认为他没出息
...but I don't agree that he's no good.
克里夫不过只是克里夫 没什么
Cleve is Cleve, that's all.
你真是令人捉摸不透的女人 普莱斯考特小姐
You're a perplexin' woman, Miss Prescott.
当一只臭鼬需要被杀死时…
When a skunk needs killin'...
怎么能说臭鼬不过只是臭鼬
...it ain't enough just to say a skunk's a skunk.
摩根先生
我这一生总是梦想嫁给有钱人
All my life I wanted to marry a rich husband.
我难道能怪克里夫只想娶有钱老婆？
Can I blame Cleve for wantin' to marry a rich wife?
我们俩都出自贫穷家庭…
Both of us may have been born for the poor house...
但我们却都不甘于贫穷
...but we're not the kind to like it.
你所说的这番话是出自内心 还是你随口说说的？告诉我实话
You believe all this you've been sayin', or is it just words? Now, tell me the truth.
实情是…
The truth is...
克里夫和我无法光靠爱情过日子
...Cleve and I couldn't live alone just on love...
我们活不了五分钟
...not for five minutes.
那么你已经回答了我在两千哩路上 不停问我自己的问题
Then you've answered the question I've been asking for better than 2,000 miles.
我有一间你见过最大的农场
I've got the biggest ranch you ever did see.
大到一整天都逛不尽
You can't ride across it in a day.
那些土地很快将换成大把钞票
That land's gonna mean money sooner than you think.
你想要个有钱丈夫…
You want a rich husband...
他就在你面前
...you're lookin' at him.
你什么都不用做 只要负责养孩子就好
There ain't a blessed thing you have to do except mind the kids.
很抱歉…
I'm sorry.
现在不行
Not now.
以后也不行
Not ever.
真是可惜…
What a waste.
像你这样条件的女人
Someone put together, like you.
艾姬
Aggie.
那些发大财的人 用金钱享尽荣华富贵
Those who struck it rich wanted all the pleasures that money could buy...
他们要买的东西数都数不尽
...and there were plenty to sell to them.
即便在沙加缅度的游船上 也充斥着奢华气氛
Even the Sacramento riverboats took on luxury goods.
我跟
I'll see it.
该你了
It's up to you.
下注？
Bettin'?
你怎么了？
What's the matter with you?
- 我打烊了 - 打烊？
-I'm checkin' out. -Checkin' out?
他怎么回事？
What's the matter with him?
走吧，走吧
"Come, come
有一片神奇的土地
"There's a wondrous land
我将在哪里给你建一个家
"Where I'll build you a home
在荒草上
"In the meadow
星星，星星
"The stars, the stars
哦，它们闪耀得多么明亮
"Oh, how bright they'll shine
在同一片领域成为领主
"On a world the Lord
西部为拓荒者成为有产者而设计
"Must have helped design
星星，星星
"The stars, the stars
哦，它们闪耀得多么明亮
"Oh, how bright they'll shine
我们的家将在那里建立
"On that home we will build
在荒草上
"In the meadow
来吧，来吧
"Come, come
这有一片奇妙的土地
"There's a wondrous land
为了充满希望的心
"For the hopeful heart
心甘情愿用手付出勤劳
"For the willing hand
来吧，来吧
"Come, come
这有一片神奇的土地
"There's a wondrous land
我将在哪里给你建一个家
"Where I'll build you a home
在荒草上
"In the meadow! "
莉莉，我必须和你谈谈
Lily, I got to talk to you.
我刚才手气正好 但我却打烊不玩了
I found myself throwing in a winning hand.
我从未想过我会为任何女孩那样做
I just never thought I'd do that for any girl.
莉莉
你可愿意和一个 没出息的赌徒在一起？
How would you like to hook up with a no-good gambler?
喔，亲爱的，咱们走吧 我这里有一千两百元
Oh, Hon, we are on our way. I got $1,200 right here.
- 我们要怎么花，开一间赌场？ - 不
-What'll we do, open a gambling house? -No.
一个已婚的男人晚上应该待在家里
A married man should spend his evenings at home.
那我们到旧金山开一家歌厅
Well, then we'll open a music hall in San Francisco.
- 不 - 我还能唱歌跳舞
-I can still sing and dance. -No.
不行，已婚的女人 晚上应该待在家里
A married woman should spend her evenings at home.
- 可是我们不能光坐在家里花钱… - 莉莉…
But we can't sit at home on $1,200 forever.
你去过旧金山吗？
Have you seen San Francisco?
那里又丑又小 到处都是跳蚤
It's ugly, and it's small, and it's full of fleas.
每五分钟就被大火烧掉…
It burns down about every five minutes...
每次它再度重建都比之前更大更棒
...but each time they keep on rebuilding it a little bigger and better than before.
那里生气蓬勃 没有任何事情能阻挡它
It's alive and kicking and nothin' can stop it.
让人想要在那里进行建设
And it makes you want to build somethin', too.
一家铁路公司
A railroad.
一家蒸汽船公司
A steamship line.
能帮助宝宝成长的地方
Somethin' to help the baby grow.
克里夫，就用那一千两百元？
Cleve, on $1,200?
我们可以先从经营篷车或 划桨船公司开始
But we could start out with a wagon or a rowboat.
只要动点脑筋 我敢打赌我们一定能成功的
With the help of the devil, I bet we'll make it.
（中场）
（进场）
年轻的美国不仅是东部与西部的结合
Young America was not only a union of East and West.
另外还有北部和南部
There were North and South, too.
然而南北之间的关系却愈来愈薄弱
And between them the bonds were weakening.
从国会议员退休的林肯先生 现在正从事律师的工作…
Mr. Lincoln, now retired from Congress and practicing law...
他意识到南部将会抵抗…
...realized that the South would fight...
并企图建立他们自己的疆土与形象
...to mold the new and uncommitted territories to its own image.
离他上任总统仍有两年…
Still, two years from the presidency...
他誓言要解放西部 并让它保持自由…
...he pleaded that the free West be allowed to remain free...
并为国家即将瓦解分裂的现象 提出警告
...and warned of the hazards of a house divided against itself.
可是南部眼见他们的 影响势力慢慢减弱…
But the South...
...seeing it's power and influence wane...
在许多西部城镇里进行 各种抗争活动
...struggled against the inevitable in dozens of Western towns.
内战的仇恨种子 因此逐渐生根发芽
And slowly, the bitter seeds of civil war took root.
你好，罗林太太
Howdy, Mrs. Rawlings.
哇！马儿！哇！
Whoa, Rosebud.
皮特森先生
Hey, Mr. Peterson.
你穿这身衣服是什么？
What's that suit you got on?
制服啊，罗林太大
Uniform, Mrs. Rawlings.
这是制服
A uniform.
我们的国民军已宣誓加入…
Our militia company was sworn in.
我现在是下士皮特森 俄亥俄州自愿军
I'm Corporal Peterson now, Ohio Volunteers.
你将有一阵子不会看到我
You won't be seein' me for a spell.
有一封信是给你的 从加州寄来的
Hey, I got a letter for you, from way out in California.
一定是我妹妹莉莉丝
It must be from my sister, Lilith.
“亲爱的伊芙…”
"Dear Eve...."
皮特森先生，你能不能等一下？
Mr. Peterson, could you wait a minute?
我想马上回信给她
I wanna answer this right away.
齐伯？
齐伯，过来一下
Zeb, come on down here.
我们希望齐伯能和我们一起去
We was hopin' Zeb might be goin' with us.
他爸在号角吹第一声时便出发了
Pa went when the first bugle blew.
那还不够吗？
Ain't one enough?
嗨，下士
Hi, Corporal.
杰若迈亚，去拿脱脂奶油给皮特森先生
Jeremiah, give Mr. Peterson some buttermilk.
脱脂奶油
Buttermilk!
是你莉莉丝阿姨写来的
It's from your Aunt Lilith.
她说在加州没有战争 他们说将来也不会有战争
Says there ain't no war out in California and they don't expect there'll be one.
“生意做得很好”
"Business is brisk.
“对活力充沛的年轻人而言 有许多工作机会”
"Many opportunities for an energetic young man."
他们正打算搭建一条铁路
There's talk of building a railroad east.
“克里夫正在努力打通关系”
"Cleve has hopes of gettin' in on the ground floor.
“如果齐伯想过来，我们很欢迎他”
"We would welcome Zeb if he wants to come."
妈，你写信和她谈我的事？
Ma, did you write her about me?
- 没有啦
Not exactly--
- 有没有？
Now, did you?
我告诉她你不喜欢务农 就和爸一样
I told her you didn't like farmin' any better than your pa did.
妈，你对这场战争的看法不正确
Ma, you got the wrong idea about this war.
并不是很糟的，是吧，下士？
It ain't gonna be so bad, is it, Corporal?
你知道爸出征报效国家
You know, Pa's havin' the time of his life.
罗林太太 是上校亲口告诉我的…
Now, Mrs. Rawlings, I got it from the captain himself...
我们短时间不可能会撤退的
...that we ain't gonna be gone no time at all.
我上不上战场，爸都由你决定  但你知道他内心是怎么想的
Pa left it up to you whether I go or not. But you know what he really felt.
罗林太太，成天在锄犁后面踩踏 根本没啥光荣可言
Mrs. Rawlings, there ain't much glory in trompin' behind a plow.
我想这封信就不急着回了
I reckon there's no hurry in answerin' this letter.
多谢你等候
Thank you for waitin'.
你是说我能去罗？
You mean I can go?
喔，有好多事要做
Well, there'll be things to do.
妈…
Ma....
我得帮你洗内裤 补袜子的破洞
I've gotta get your underwear washed and your socks darned.
他们会给你那种衣服吗？
Do they give you one of them suits?
那种制服？
One of them uniforms?
会的
I reckon.
可能不会给你衬衣
They might not give you no shirts though.
把那件脱下来 我帮你洗
Take that one off. I'll wash it for you.
我已经洗了其他几件 还没烫过呢
I got the others washed but they aren't ironed yet.
母亲，我…
Mother, I....
你为什么那样叫我？
Why'd you call me that?
你总是喊我“妈”
It's always been Ma before.
不晓得…
I don't know.
突然间…
All of a sudden...
喊“妈”似乎已经不够了
...Ma didn't seem enough somehow.
嘿！小子！
Yahoo. Hey, cowpoke!
回去！狗狗！
Go on back, dog.
回去！
Go on!
我能怎么办，爸？
What could I do, Pa?
他是奈勒斯的儿子
He's Linus' boy.
从小到大就像奈勒斯
Always was more Linus' blood.
所以我才会那么爱他吧
I guess that's why I love him so much.
但您得帮我祈祷，爸…
But you've got to help me pray, Pa.
帮我祈祷
Help me pray.
俄亥俄！
Ohio.
俄亥俄州炮兵连队！
Battery "B", Ohio.
- 走吧！ - 快点！
-Let's go! -On the double. Come on.
有谁是密西根州的第十二连队？
Anybody here from the Twelfth Michigan?
印地安那州的三十六连队
Thirty-sixth Indiana.
1862年4月6日夜里…
Evening of April Sixth, 1862.
响彻云霄一整天的枪炮 现在恢复宁静…
The guns that had roared all day fell silent...
就在一间叫做沙罗会议厅 的小教堂旁边的
...around a little church called the Shiloh Meeting House.
许多人在那星期日都见到了上帝…
Many a man had met his God that Sunday...
只是不是在教堂里
...but not in church.
你等于在浪费时间 他已经死了
You wasted your time, men. He's dead.
- 不，医生，他是罗林上校
But, Doc, this here is Captain Rawlings!
- 奈勒斯罗林上校
Captain Linus Rawlings.
- 把他带出去 - 走吧
-Take him out. -Keep movin', men.
- 你走路干嘛不长眼睛？
Why can't you look where you're goin'?
- 对不起，士兵
I'm sorry, soldier.
小心点！
Watch it.
铁锯…白兰地…
Saw. Brandy.
麻醉剂
Chloroform.
全部都拿来
Get it all down.
全拿来！
Come on, all of it!
走吧，我们在这里只会碍事
Come on. We're just in the way here.
那是西区战事前线最血腥的一天
It had been the bloodiest day of the war on the Western front.
白天看起来好像邦联大获全胜
In the morning, it had looked like a Confederate victory...
但是一到晚上…
...but by nightfall...
再也没有人提到 “赢”或“输”这几个字眼
...no man cared to use the words "win" or "lose".
在沙罗会议厅之后…
After Shiloh...
南方军从未展开笑颜
...the South never smiled.
- 你有没有尝过这个水？ - 没有
You tasted that water yet?
尝尝看
-No. -Well, try it.
- 味道怪怪的，是吧？ - 是啊
-Tastes funny, huh? -Yeah.
太阳下山之前 水是粉红色的
I seen it before sundown. It was pink.
比黄樟茶还要红
Pinker than sassafras tea.
你是说…？
You mean...?
头脑正常的人不应该会喝这种水
It don't seem fittin' a man should have to drink water like that.
头脑正常的人不应该会做出 咱们今天做过的事
Don't seem fittin' a man should have to do any of the things we've done today.
你有没有杀人？
Did you kill anybody?
应该没有
I don't think so.
我一开始就被人打昏
I got knocked dizzy right off.
当我醒来之后找到我的枪 已经被弄坏了
Then when I come to and found my rifle, it was busted.
然后来了几个士兵拿东西刺我的手
Then some more soldiers come along and tried to stick me in the arm.
剩下来的部分都全混在一起了
All the rest is, is mixed up after that.
我也没杀任何人 我不想杀人
I ain't killed nobody, neither. And I don't want to.
- 你打哪来的？ - 俄亥俄州
-Hey, where you from? -Ohio.
这场蠢战争从东部开打 咱们西部的人干嘛淌这混水？
This fool war started in the East. What's us Westerners doin' in it?
我再也搞不清楚了！
I don't rightly know any more!
和我原来想的不太一样
It ain't quite what I expected.
一个开膛破肚的人 哪有任何光荣可言
There ain't much glory in lookin' at a man with his guts hangin' out.
- 你打哪来的？ - 德州
-Where you from? -Texas.
我说啊…
Say....
你该不会是南方军的人吧？
You ain't a Reb, are you?
今天早上我是的 今晚我就不确定了
Well, I was this mornin'. Tonight, I ain't so sure.
我好像应该得对你开枪
It seems like, I oughta be shootin' you.
你有东西可以射杀我吗？
Well, you got anything to shoot with?
没有
No.
我只有这把刺刀
All I got's this bayonet.
我有一把手枪
I got a pistol.
我从一个阵亡军官身上拿到的
I took it off a dead officer.
咱们何不溜出这里？
Hey, why don't we skedaddle out of here?
- 你是说弃职潜逃？ - 为什么不呢？
-You mean desert? -I mean, why don't--
让那些想打仗的人去打吧
Just leave this here war to the folks who want it.
人家都说在加州没有战争
They say there ain't no war out in California.
把小队召集到这里
脱队者！快加入自己的小队！
Stragglers, join your regiment.
脱队者！嘿！你！
Stragglers! Hey, you!
我打算把卢梭小队移到这一区
I'm planning to move Rousseau's brigade into this area.
潜伏此地，在日出前部署完毕 你批准吗？
Hidden battery, placed well before dawn. Do you approve?
你所做的任何部署安排 我都批准
I'll approve any dispositions you want to make.
今天要不是你I卫侧翼 我们很可能全军覆没
If you hadn't held the flank today, we'd have been whipped for fair.
薛曼一自们坐一下 我有话要告诉你
Sherman, let's sit down a minute. There's somethin' I wanna say to you.
油灯
Lantern.
接下来可能由你独挑大梁了
You may find yourself in command here.
为什么？
Why?
我看过今天发刊的新闻报纸文章
I've seen some of the dispatches the newspaper correspondents...
...have filed today.
他们说今天早上的突袭 出乎我意料之外
They're sayin' I was taken by surprise this morning.
那并未出乎你意料之外
You weren't taken by surprise.
我有
I was.
不管怎样…
No matter.
他们说…
They're sayin'...
我昨晚又喝醉酒了
...I was drunk again last night.
你有吗？
Were you?
没有
No.
但是蜡烛两头烧根本行不通
But you can't fight front and rear.
明天无论打输或打赢…
Win or lose, tomorrow...
我都要辞职
...I intend to resign.
就因为报纸的那些文章？
Because of the newspapers?
因为大众对我缺乏信心
Because of the general lack of confidence in me.
喔，你以为我从未有过那种感受？
Don't you think I've ever felt like that?
一个月前他们骂我是 疯子，脑筋不正常
A month ago they were sayin' I was crazy. Insane.
现在他们夸我是大英雄 不管是疯子或英雄，我还是我
And now they're callin' me a hero. Hero or crazy, I'm the same man.
无论别人怎么想
It doesn't matter what the people think.
都是你自己想的，格兰特
It's what you think, Grant.
那就是格兰特？
You mean that's Grant?
是的
I reckon.
格兰特将军
General Grant.
这场战争将在西部取得胜利 如何取得胜利…
You know this war is gonna be won in the West and how to win it.
要由你的所作所为去证实
Everything you've done proves it.
一个人只有在做错事时 才有资格辞职
And I say that a man has the right to resign only if he's wrong.
做对事时便没有资格
Not if he's right.
我想我从来没那样想过
I guess I never thought of it that way.
我会好好考虑的
I'll think it over.
还有什么好考虑的？
What is there to think about?
军队有你在是比较好的 那便是一种考验
The Army's better off with you than without you. That's the test.
好吧
All right.
谢谢
Thanks.
日出之前有很多事要做，薛曼
There's a lot to do before morning, Sherman?
你在做什么？
What are you doin'?
你为什么逼我那么做？
Why'd you make me do that?
开火！
"When Johnny comes marching home again Hurrah, hurrah
"We'll give him a hearty welcome and Hurrah, hurrah
"The men will cheer, the boys will shout The ladies they will all turn out
"And we'll all feel gay When Johnny comes marching home
"Get ready to join the jubilee Hurrah, hurrah
"We'll drink up a toast, or two, or three Hurrah, hurrah
"The band will play and we'll sing for joy And all the ladies will kiss the boys
"And we'll all feel gay When Johnny comes marching home
"The men will cheer, the boys will shout"
（奈勒斯罗林 1810年至1862年）
（伊芙普莱斯考特罗林）
嘿，齐伯！
Hey, Zeb.
你没收到我的信？
Didn't you get my letter?
我四个多月前寄出的
I wrote more than four months ago.
在得知爸爸的消息之后…
She never was...
她整个人便再也不复从前
...quite the same after she got the news about Pa.
我觉得她并不害怕死亡，齐伯 只是…
I don't think she minded goin', Zeb, except...
她当时很想再见你一面
...she wanted to see you again.
当然，爸爸的尸骨并不在那里
'Course Pa ain't really there.
我还是立了一个碑
I put up a stone anyway.
好吧…
我得上路了
I'd better be on my way.
上路？去哪？
Way? Where?
我需要你，齐伯
I need you, Zeb.
我回来只为了一件事…
Only one thing brought me back...
她…
...and she's....
这个农场有一半是你的
Well, this farm is half yours.
我在想我们好不容易清出 河边的那条道路…
I'm thinkin' we'd finally clear away that patch of woods down by the river....
你比我还懂得处理农场的事 你并不需要我
You're twice the farmer I am. You don't need me.
农场是你的了 这样才公平
That farm's all yours. That's only fair.
这样我还是觉得不太好
I sure don't feel right about this.
那你打算去哪里？
What are you gonna do?
我还不晓得
I haven't mustered out yet.
我还可以转任当普通警官
I can still transfer to the regulars.
或许到西部当骑警
The cavalry, maybe. And go West.
去和印地安人对抗？
And have to fight Indians?
我真的很不了解你，齐伯
You sure are hard to make out, Zeb.
你干嘛要那么做？ 你喜欢打架吗？
Now, what do you wanna do that for? Do you like fightin'?
你还记得爸曾经告诉我们 他对抗大熊的故事吗？
Do you remember the story Pa used to tell us about fightin' that grizzly bear?
记得
Yeah.
我问他：“你为什么要做出那种事？”
And I asked him. I said: "Now, why'd you get in such a fix?
“你喜欢和大熊打架吗？”
"Do you like fightin' grizzlies?"
他说…
He said:
“那倒也不是…”
"Well, not 'specially.
“我只是想到外面闯 结果那只熊比我先到那里”
"I just wanted to go somewhere and the bear was there first."
所以我…
我想我也要出去闯了
I guess I just wanna go somewhere, too.
- 再会 - 再会，齐伯
-So long. -So long, Zeb.
正当北部和南部成分裂局势时…
Even while North and South were being torn apart...
东部和西部却慢慢统合 透过《驿马快递》…
...East and West had been drawn together by the Pony Express...
有史以来最危险的通邮服务
...the most daring mail route in history.
八十名骑士着邮包 风雨无阻，日以继夜地奔驰…
Eighty riders were in the saddle at all times, night and day, in all weather.
一半往东骑 一半往西骑…
Half of them riding east, half riding west...
来回于密苏里和沙加缅度之间
...between Missouri and Sacramento...
让邮件于几天内寄达 不用再花几个月时间
...carrying mail cross-country in days instead of months.
他们不配武器，只为轻便成行
Unarmed, they rode to save weight.
一封信邮费五元 只能寄薄薄的信纸
Five dollars a letter, the mail cost, and on thin paper, too.
这项服务代表着勇气 技术以及速度…
It was courage, skill and speed...
对抗充满敌意的印地安人，土匪 有时还得应付洪水
...against hostile Indians, bandits, hell and occasional high water.
在他们奔驰的同时 人们另外开始搭建…
Even as they rode, men were already building a faster...
更快速的横贯全国的 《大陆电报线路》
...message carrier across the country, the Overland Telegraph.
结果让印地安人找到新的娱乐
And the Indians found a new amusement...
聆听电线传送出的歌唱声音
...listening to the level tune of the singing wires.
可是印地安人却对另一件事 感到不快…
But far less amusing to the Indians...
即有铁马之称的火车铁路的到来
...was the coming of the steel roadway of the Iron Horse.
铁道路线预定经过 伟大的天然屏障：洛矶山脉…
The surveyors' route lay through immense natural barriers, the Rocky Mountains...
以及同样令人生畏的喜耶亚山区
...and the equally discouraging High Sierras.
然而浩瀚的崇山峻岭并无法阻挡 两家大企业…
But range upon range could never stop the titanic contest...
争先建造有史以来…
...between two corporate giants racing to put down...
最长的铁道 最后将交会会合
...the greatest mileage of track before they met:
《中太平洋公司》负责从沙加缅度 往东至喜耶亚山区
The Central Pacific eastward from Sacramento through the Sierras.
《联合太平洋公司》则横跨整个 西向平原区…
And the Union Pacific, forging westward across the plains...
但仍需克服洛矶山脉的屏障
...with the Rockies still to come.
这场竞赛的奖赏是免费土地 铁道所到之处便可获得当地广大土地
The prize in the race was free land, vast parcels for every mile of track laid.
将来有天，那些土地将价值百万
Land that would one day be worth millions.
停止
Hold it!
放下！
Set it down!
工人们，站起来！
Up!
你在哪找到的？
Where'd you find 'em?
差不多一哩之外
'Bout a mile back yonder.
- 是强尼霍马兹 - 那是杰克帕金
That's Johnny Hormatz. And Jack Perkins.
在搞什么？野餐吗？
What the hell is this? A picnic?
- 印地安人杀了我们的几个人
The Indians got a couple of our men--
- 先生，你之前是工头…
Mister, you were the foreman here. Now you're a tracklayer.
现在你沦为小工 大家全给我回去工作！
Now get back to work, all of you!
快点！
Move it!
快！
Fast!
- 你 - 是的
-You. -Yes, sir?
你现在成了工头 直到我找到更棒的人取代你
You're the new foreman, till I find somebody better. Now get 'em at it!
- 遵命 - 快叫他们做事！
-Wait a minute. -Move it!
- 等一下 - 快点！
你叫杰梭罗史都瓦特？
Is your name Jethro Stuart?
好，快点工作！
Mr. Jethro Stuart, you're hired to hunt buffalo to feed these men...
杰梭罗史都瓦特先生 你的工作是去猎水牛喂这些工人…
不是阻挠他们做事 你干嘛把尸体带回来？
...not to stop their work. Why'd you bring these bodies here?
我想铁路公司的人或许会有兴趣
They're railroaders. I thought somebody on the railroad might be interested.
我就是铁路公司的人 我一点兴趣都没有
I'm the railroad, and I'm not interested.
你应该就地埋掉 然后找出杀他们的印地安人
You should've buried 'em, then tracked down the Indians who did it.
金先生，就像你说的 我的工作是猎水牛
Mr. King, like you said, I was hired to hunt, not to dig graves or fight Indians.
不是挖坟墓 或去对付印地安人
这些人多半是退伍军人 几具尸体应该不会 让他们感到不适吧
Those fellas are mostly old soldiers. Two dead men shouldn't bother 'em much.
除了工作，我不要他们有其他想法 你了解吗？
I don't want anything in their thick skulls but their work. Do you understand?
把那些尸体弄掉 开始去追查涉嫌的印地安人
Now get rid of those bodies and start trackin' those Indians.
你真是贵人多忘事，金先生 我的工作是猎水牛
You keep forgettin', Mr. King, my job's buffalo.
已经不是了
It was buffalo.
去找会计，把你的工时算一算
Go to the paymaster and draw your time.
刚才那个工头你并没开除他
That foreman fella, you didn't fire him.
你只是降他的职 因为你需要他
You just took him down a peg 'cause you needed him.
现在谁来负责猎水牛？你吗？
Who's gonna shoot buffalo? You?
- 那是什么鬼？ - 牛奶
-What the devil is that? -Milk.
牛奶？
Milk?
看来我退伍之后 军队改变了不少
The Army must've changed since I was in it.
- 我刚到，我饿了 - 是吗？
-I just rode in. I'm hungry. -You are, huh?
但你宁可看他们吃东西
But you'd rather watch them than eat.
- 是这样吗？ - 是的
-Is that it? -That's it.
希望你是全力以赴在保护这条铁路
I wish you were as eager to protect this railroad.
你有没有听说 今天有两个人被杀？
Did you get any word about the two men who where killed today?
我找到阿拉巴赫族的人 并和他们酋长谈过
I tracked the Arapahoes and talked to the chief.
那两个人擅入禁区一哩内
They were a mile off the right-of-way where they had no business...
他们无权酒醉跑进那里 调戏印地安女人
...drunk and chasin' squaws.
- 他们和印地安人一样有错 - 是这样吗？
It was as much their fault as it was the Indians'.
阿兵哥，你的任务是对抗印地安人 不是和他们和谈
Well, soldier boy, your job is to fight Indians, not to agree with 'em.
金先生，当时有两百个阿拉巴赫人 我只有二十名手下
Mr. King, there were 200 Arapahoes and I had 20 men.
对我而言…
Now, to me...
和谈是比对抗更为明智的选择
...agreein' seemed wiser than fightin'.
对你而言？
To you, huh?
或许我应该给上校派一份电报过去
You know, I might just send off a wire to the colonel.
他或许不会同意你的做法
He may not agree.
我已经呈报过 他也同意了
I already reported it. He does agree.
讯息已接收并知晓… 士兵
Acknowledged and understood. Sergeant.
有麻烦吗，长官？
Trouble, sir?
我不知道
I don't know.
嘿，队长
Hey, Lieutenant.
我刚收到讯息 印地安人打算发动攻击
I just got a message the Indians are up to something.
你可知情？
Do you know anything about it?
酋长说铁路公司毁约
The chief says the railroad's busted the agreement.
要改变路径 得从亚拉帕霍人的狩猎区经过
They've changed the route and are comin' through the Arapahoe huntin' grounds.
- 你确定酋长没说错？ - 确定
-You sure the chief's right? -Plenty sure.
他们已经准备开战了
They're getting the warpaint ready.
你的意思是说…
Can you stand there and tell me...
一点小改变就会让 阿拉巴赫族少一头水牛…
...that one little change is gonna cost the Arapahoes one buffalo.
- 或者甚至少一头野兔？ - 金先生…
-Or even one jackrabbit? -Mr. King!
他们或许会觉得有所出入 但没有人要伤害他们啊！
They can be made to see it differently. Who's hurting 'em?
铁路到底是啥玩意？ 只不过是两条铁道和一个大哨子
What's a railroad anyway? Two tracks and a whistle.
他们怕的不是铁道 而是铁道即将带来的东西
It's not the tracks they're afraid of. It's what the tracks bring.
水牛猎人猎杀他们的畜兽
The buffalo hunters slaughtering off their herds.
接下来拓荒者抵达之后…
And then the settlers coming in.
那到等到何时？ 二十，三十年之后？
And when will that be? Twenty, 30 years, maybe?
那个时候我们全都死了
By then, we'll all be dead.
现在我们只要横跨这片土地
Right now we're just crossing the land.
就这样，在我们有生之年 阿拉巴赫族的土地不会有事
That's all. Land that's safe to the Arapahoes for our lifetime.
你去和他们谈
Now, you go talk to 'em. Smoke a peacepipe with 'em.
和他们抽抽和平烟 随他们怎样都好
主要是和他们拟定新合约
Just get 'em to make a new agreement.
那是你的任务不是吗？ 维持和平？
That's your job, isn't it? Keeping the peace?
我会维持和平的，金先生
I'll keep the peace, Mr. King...
但你也必须信守承诺
...if you keep your promise.
听说你姓罗林 你是俄亥俄州人
Hear your name's Rawlings and you're from Ohio.
你爸该不会是叫奈勒斯罗林吧？
Your pa's name couldn't be Linus Rawlings, could it?
- 是的 - 我认识他
-Could be. -Knew him.
我是杰梭罗史都瓦特
Jethro Stuart.
- 他曾经提过你 - “曾经”？
-He used to speak of you. -Used to?
爸在沙罗殉身
Pa was killed at Shiloh.
请坐，史都瓦特先生
Sit down, Mr. Stuart.
至少强过死在锄犁后面
Well, better than dyin' behind a plow.
我曾经试图安定过一年
I tried it. Settled down for a year once.
害我少了十年寿命
It took ten years off my life.
你妈妈…
Your ma....
她一定很特别 才能让奈勒斯甘心定下来
She must've been somethin' real special gettin' old Linus to stay put.
她是的，史都瓦特先生 她很特别
She was, Mr. Stuart. Very special.
这个老奈勒斯…
Old Linus.
有两午时间 你爸和我曾经一起捕兽皮…
Two years runnin' once, your pa and me trapped together. Up along the Wannakee.
就在望纳比那边
抓到好多海狸 多到必须将他们尾巴绑起来…
We got ourselves so many beaver...
才能把它们拖下山
...we had to tie 'em tail-to-tail just to drag 'em down the mountain.
有一哩长呢 那些海狸皮毛
Over a mile long it was, that line of beaver pelts.
史都瓦特先生，我父亲可以把事实 加油添醋讲成六种版本
Mr. Stuart, my father could take the truth and stretch it about six ways.
你的口气和他好像
You sound just like him.
我想你这番话应该是赞美的意思
I'll take it you meant that kindly.
我可不敢随便说你是个骗子
Well, I'd think twice before I called you a liar.
提到骗子 我要问你一下…
Tell me somethin', talkin' about liars:
为什么奈勒斯的儿子会和 麦克金这种人在一起？
Why would a son of old Linus get mixed up with a man like Mike King?
我知道你的意思
I know what you mean.
但麦克金并不代表铁路
But Mike King isn't the railroad.
我不认为他知道这一点
I don't think he knows that.
他要把路线改回去，是吧？
He's changin' the route back, is he?
没有
No.
我知道…
I know.
但他会不择手段 只为了比《中太平洋公司》抢先一天
But he'd do anything to gain a day on the Central Pacific.
他不是笨蛋，
But he's not a fool. He doesn't want a war.
他不想开战 阿拉巴赫族也不想
And neither do the Arapahoes.
我想我应该可以说服他们同意 改变铁道路线…
I think I could get them to agree to this change in route if...
如果我可以和他们坐下来好好聊一聊
...I could just sit down and talk with them for a while.
- 你要怎么做？ - 这便是问题所在
-How're you gonna get 'em to do it? -That's just it.
我需要一个懂他们语言 而且他们能信赖的人
I need somebody that knows the language and that they trust.
你有没有认识像这样的人 史都瓦特先生？
You wouldn't happen to know someone like that, would you, Mr. Stuart?
你老爸设陷阱的手段无人能比…
Your pa could set a trap like no man I ever come across.
慢慢引他们上钩，然后…
Just coax 'em on, and wham!
你最好做点表态动作 好让他确定你不会食言
You'd better do somethin', so he'll know you're pledgin' your word.
那该死的哨声听起来好像 命运索魂令
That blame whistle's like the crack of doom from all that's natural.
我妈总认为人应该在土地上 留点记号
My ma felt a man oughta make his scratch on the land...
在离开时 留下不同风貌
...and leave it a little different than when he come.
总之，谢谢你帮我处理酋长的事
Anyway, thanks for fixin' things with the chief.
我？我可没处理什么事
Me? I fixed nothin'.
我只是代你传话罢了 并不代表能事成
You put the words in my mouth but that won't make 'em come true.
杰梭罗，我说过我必须维持和平
I said what I had to, to keep the peace. I know there's a risk.
- 我知道会有风险 - 风险？
Risks? Maybe you don't understand.
或许你并不明白
你刚才已经郑重承诺你的话
You pledged your word back there. Not mine, not the Army's...
那不是我的，不是军队的 也不是铁路公司的话
...not the railroad's.
是你告诉他们 他们能够保有原来的狩猎之地
It was your word that told 'em they'd keep their huntin' grounds.
- 我认为他们会的
I think they will.
- 我认为你好比把头伸出去…
I think you've got your neck stuck out like a prairie chicken...
像一只待宰的鸡 等着人来宰你的头
...waitin' for one side or the other to chop it off.
你老爸当初和我一再地被人 赶出荒地…
Your pa and me got kicked out of one territory after another...
一堆人蜂拥而至 终结狩猎，建设乡镇
...with people pourin' in, killin' off game, puttin' up towns....
这股风潮是不会停止的
It ain't gonna stop.
你的合约将会被人破坏 我不想留在这里看它发生
Your treaty's gonna get broken and I don't wanna be around to see it happen.
等你受够了之后再来找我吧
Look me up when you get your bellyful.
- 你要去哪？ - 回去山上
-Where you goin'? -Back to the mountains.
与世隔绝的山上 完全没有人烟的地方
To the high lonesome where there ain't no people at all yet.
再会
So long.
现在《中太平洋公司》已穿越 喜耶亚山区的屏障…
By now the Central Pacific had broken through the wall of the High Sierras...
疲惫不堪地往东经过 平坦的内华达州
...and was straining eastward across the flatlands of Nevada.
而《联合太平洋公司》 多亏与印地安人之间的长期和平相处…
While the Union Pacific, thanks to its long peace with the Indians...
才能够轻松面对庞大压力 士气高昂地朝另一方向前进
...was able to keep up pressure just as avidly in the opposite direction.
这场竞争十分刺激 但也同时花费不少…
The competition was exciting, but also costly...
两家公司都迫不及待想从 已经架设好的铁道开始赚取获利
...and both companies were itching to earn money from tracks already laid.
- 马儿情况还好吧，杰克？ - 我刚骑时不太好
-Did the horses ride all right, Jake? -No better than I did.
必须让他们休息一天 才能出发去猎兔子或水牛
We'll have to rest 'em a day before we can start huntin' rabbits, much less buffalo.
立刻牵他们去喝水
Let's get 'em to water right away.
你说不会有水牛猎人来
You say no buffalo hunter come.
白人都是骗子
White man, liar.
我们再也不替你们侦察了
We scout for you no more!
你说我们活着的时候都不会来
Not in our lifetime, you said.
结果跑来一堆水牛猎人和拓荒者
And there they are. The buffalo slaughterers and the settlers.
好啦，是比我预料得早
All right, it's sooner than I figured.
但铁路公司没钱了 他们需要钱继续运作
But the railroad's broke. They need money to keep movin' on.
没有人力就没有钱 没有钱就没有铁路
No people, no money. No money, no railroad.
- 就这么简单 - 那阿拉巴赫族呢？
-It's as simple as that, Lieutenant. -What about the Arapahoes?
瞧瞧这些人 有半数的人都是从欧洲来的
Take a look at those people. Half of 'em straight from Europe.
他们会很辛苦 但他们能熬过的
They'll have a rough time but they'll make it.
你知道他们为何能熬过？
And do you wanna know why they'll make it?
因为他们肯变通 肯改变自己的生活方式
Because they're willing to change their ways.
阿拉巴赫族也得改变生活方式才行 如果不肯，他们就完蛋了
The Arapahoes will have to change, too. If they don't, they're finished.
我知道他们必须改变 将来有天这片土地将被占领…
I know they have to change and some day the land'll be taken over...
被这些农夫的城镇和牲畜占领
...by these farmers with their towns and their cattle.
可是不能像这样
But, not like this.
他们没有必要被人摆弄 而我不想被卷入其中
They don't have to be double-crossed, and I don't have to be a part of it!
你不想，队长？
You don't, Lieutenant?
你忘记你身上这套制服了？
Aren't you forgetting that uniform?
没错，金先生，我是想忘掉
That's right, Mr. King, I'm forgetting it!
如果军队在这里没有任何权限 那我现在就要辞职
If the Army hasn't got any authority out here, I'm resigning. And, now!
我不认为那样对阿拉巴赫族 有任何帮助
I don't see how that's gonna help the Arapahoes.
没有任何事能帮助他们
Nothing'll help 'em.
但也没有任何事情能阻止他们
But nothing's gonna stop 'em.
印地安人来袭！
Indian attack!
印地安人来袭！找掩护！
你看看…
Take a good look!
你想要战争，你可如愿了 我希望你是第一个赔上性命的人
You wanted a war, and you got one. I hope you're the first man killed in it.
把篷车调头！
Turn those wagons over!
对准领先的马匹开枪 先拿下酋长！
Shoot for the lead horses. Sergeant, take over.
罗林，你用这个
Rawlings, try that.
印地安人故意让水牛狂奔逃窜
The Indians are stampeding the buffalo.
卑鄙小人！ 来吧
Dirty skunks! Come on!
我告诉过你不会有战争
I told you there'd be no war.
瞧瞧他们
Look at 'em.
他们撤退了
They've quit.
他们会再回来的
They'll be back.
他们派来野兽来杀死 他们称为“铁马”的怪兽
They just sent a bunch of animals to kill an animal they call the "Iron Horse".
但那怪兽仍在，可不是？
Well, it's still standin', isn't it?
没有任何事情能阻止它
And nothin's gonna stop it.
你看到那样 你的日子还过得下去吗？
You think you can live with that?
我可以与这情况共生共亡！
I can live with it, or I can die with it.
你听看看…
Just listen!
你这样还能过得下去吗？
You can live with that?
那个？
That?
那才不是哭声
That ain't cryin'.
那只是新生命继续存活的声音
That's just new life goin' on.
把这女人扶起来 然后把其他受伤的人抬进帐篷里
Pick up this woman and put the rest of the engine in the shed.
嘿，马文…剩下的人回去工作！ 我们还得继续造铁路！
The rest of you, back to work. We've got a railroad to build.
这个嘛…
看来你终于已经受够了
It looks like you finally got your bellyful.
哈罗，杰梭罗
Hello, Jethro.
看来你过得还不错
Appears you're doin' well.
还可以
Can't complain.
溪里满满都是海狸 争先恐后挤进陷阱里
Creek's loaded with beavers, fightin' their way into the trap.
没有白人指使我做事
Ain't no white men lookin' over my shoulder...
印地安人都对我很友善
...and the Indians are plumb cordial.
把你的东西放进去 这地方够两个人住的
Toss your stuff in there. Plenty of room for two.
谢谢
Thanks.
你就睡在那边
You'll be bunkin' yonder.
熟悉一下环境 以便待会儿需要什么就可以找到
Better take your bearin's now, so you can find it when you need it.
你若不习惯我打呼 你明天可以自己盖一间木屋
If you don't like my snorin' you can build your own cabin tomorrow.
我帮你打点里面
I'll furnish the axe.
- 谢谢，我只是路过而已
Thanks. I'm just passin' through.
- 路过去哪？
Through to where?
你所到之处都是去过的地方
Anywhere you go is like where you've been.
你在那边受的伤害还不够？
Ain't you lost enough tail feathers back there?
我是受过一点伤
I've been plucked some.
但那便是我喜欢这个国家的原因
But that's what I like about this country.
另一座山丘的草永远都比较绿
There's always greener grass over the next hill.
打从那该死铁路经过之后 再也不是了
Not no more. Not since that damn railroad come.
所有牧草都被人管东锁了起来
All the grass is bein' staked out now, with a lock on it.
或许我得再爬高一点的山丘 才能找到
Maybe I'll just have to climb a little higher hill to find it.
要不要一起来？
How about comin' along?
你疯了？
Are you crazy?
就像印地安人说的： “这些石头和树木都不想搬家”
Like the Indians say, "These rocks and trees around here feel no call to move.
“凭什么我要搬呢？”
"Why should I?"
我或许不是印地安人，杰梭罗…
Guess I'm not an Indian, Jethro.
我也不是石头或树木…
And I'm sure not a rock nor a tree.
但物以类聚 不管愿不愿意
A man belongs with his own kind, like him or not.
铁路的来临为沿路的土地 带来了许多改变
The coming of railroads brought changes in the land through which they passed.
现在成群牛羊聚集 绵延数百哩之长…
Now, immense herds of cattle were driven hundreds of miles to meet the lines...
朝东边的市集前进
...bound for markets in the East.
原野上竖立起篱笆 牛羊被圈围起来…
Fences went up, cattle trails were barred...
畜牧业者和拓荒者之间长久以来 存在着血腥斗争…
...and a long and bloody wrangle began between cattlemen and homesteaders.
法令是由那些射枪 最快最准的人决定的
The law was in the hands of whoever could shoot fast and straight...
不过有些人也会执意出面 当法令代言人
...except where there was somebody determined to stand for law.
有些人看到羊群可能会觉得 很具有田园风光
Others might look on sheep and a shepherd as a pastoral scene.
但畜牧业者可不这么想
But not the cattleman.
对他们而言，羊把草吃光 而青草得之不易
To him, sheep destroyed grass, and grass came dear.
如果某个人的性命 比草还不值钱…
And if a man's life were held cheaper than grass...
那只会被视为战争死伤 而非触犯杀人罪
...it was considered a casualty of war, not a crime.
在所有争端事件当中
And, in all this...
唯一以寡敌众的便是那些佩戴警徽的人
...the man with the star was only one against many.
但那些非法之徒日子愈来愈难过…
But time was running out for the reckless ones...
即那些亡命之徒 那些持枪犯案的小子
...the desperadoes, the gallop-and-gunshot boys...
因为有愈来愈多老百姓 开始要求大家遵行法令
...as more and more citizens demanded respect for the law...
并以身作则随时回击 以维护法令尊严
...and showed themselves ready to fight to uphold it.
这些在西部陆续成立的新城镇 都开始梦想…
And the raw new towns that sprung up in the West began to dream...
有天能成为在金门畔 曾经被视为流氓城市的那个地方
...of becoming as refined as that one-time hooligan city by the Golden Gate.
旧金山现在变得繁华热闹…
San Francisco was now respectable.
文明优雅到甚至有人拍卖华厦
So sophisticated, in fact, it even had mansions up for auction.
两千元！
$2,000.
那是最后一次出价？
Is that your last bid?
各位先生女士 这奖杯可是纯黄金打造，还刻着…
Ladies and gentlemen, this trophy is solid gold and fully inscribed.
“克里夫凡伟伦 旧金山至堪萨斯市铁路公司董事长”
"Mr. Cleve van Valen, President of the San Francisco--Kansas City Railroad."
这可是他心爱的个人收藏
It's a treasure he held dear to his heart.
有没有人出价三千买这无价收藏？
Do I hear $3,000 for this priceless possession?
无价个头啦…
Priceless, my foot.
我们当初拿它当门挡
We used it for a doorstop.
- 两千五百元！ - 两千五百元！
$2,500.
两千五百元！
两千五百元？两千五百元卖出！
Sold. $2,500.
真是令人难过的一天，莉莉丝
It's a sad day, Lilith.
难过？
Sad?
我们大赚大花三次财富
We made and spent three fortunes together.
有什么好难过的？
What's so sad about that?
如果他再多活久一点 我们有可能再赚再花一次
If he'd lived a little longer we would've made and spent another.
- 对不起，凡伟伦夫人 - 什么事？
-I beg your pardon, Mrs. van Valen. -What?
那把椅子已经卖出了，很抱歉
The chair, it's been sold. I'm sorry.
那就拿去吧 别道歉，尽管拿去
Well then, take it. Quit apologizin' and take it.
谢谢，夫人
Thank you, madam.
如果有别的方法可以偿还债务的话…
If there had been some other way to pay off the debts....
不要紧的
It doesn't matter.
我有两件东西是没有人能拿走的…
I've got two things no one can ever take from me:
这个和我在亚利桑那州的土地
This, and my land in Arizona.
莉莉丝，我不想泼你冷水…
Lilith, I don't want to dash any hopes...
可是那农场根本不值钱
...but that ranch is nearly worthless.
但总是一块地，不是吗？
Well, it's there, isn't it?
是的，但大多数畜牲都卖掉或被偷了
Yes, but most of the cattle have been sold off or stolen.
- 牛羊再买就是了
I'll get cattle.
- 你将需要有人帮忙做事- 有人帮你经营农场
You'll need someone to work it and manage it for you.
- 我会找人的  找谁？
-I'll get that, too. -Who?
我的侄子 他在当骑警
My nephew. He's a marshal out there somewhere.
莉莉丝，你这把年纪 那种日子可能会很辛苦
Lilith, at your age it might be kind of rough.
辛苦？
Rough?
我爸妈当初为了寻找土地 在河上航行遇难而死
My ma and pa were killed goin' down the river just lookin' for land.
我想我多少还是有 普莱斯考特家的遗传
I guess I got a little of that Prescott blood in me after all.
爸？
Pa?
莉莉丝姨婆在诺布丘的家 和那一样高吗？
Is Aunt Lilith's house on Nob Hill as high as that?
我不知道，儿子
I don't know, son.
待会儿回家，你可以问莉莉丝姨婆 她会告诉你
On our way home you ask your Aunt Lilith. She'll tell you.
亲爱的？你想你认得出她吗？
Honey? Do you think you'll know her?
- 什么？
What?
- 你的莉莉丝阿姨- 你想你可以认得出她吗？
Your Aunt Lilith. Do you think you'll recognize her?
- 当然
Sure.
齐伯？怎么回事？
Zeb? What's the matter?
没事
Nothing.
走吧
Come on.
谢谢
（黄金城交界处）
- 请问你是莉莉丝姨婆吗？
Ma'am, are you our Great Aunt Lilith?
- 如果你们是齐伯的孩子，我就是
If you're Zeb's children, I am.
- 莉莉丝
Lilith.
- 齐伯
Zeb.
齐伯罗林
Zeb Rawlings.
喔，老天
Oh, goodness.
我一再叮咛自己绝对不准哭的
I swore up and down I wasn't gonna cry.
你就像妈形容的那么美丽
You're just as pretty as Ma said you was.
这位是我的太太，茱莉
I'd like you to meet my wife, Julie.
很高兴认识你
Pleased to meet you.
我也很高兴认识你
And I'm pleased to meet you, too.
我简直无法形容我有多开心
I just can't tell you how pleased.
这是伊芙，我们家的老么
This here's Eve, underneath all the jam.
- 过来见见山姆 - 山姆？
-Come on and meet Sam now. -Sam?
山姆是我们的马 他可以一次拉两台篷车喔
Sam's our horse. He could pull two wagons if he wanted.
喔，对不起，失陪了 我得去见过山姆呢
Well, if you'll excuse me, I have my orders to meet Sam.
走吧
Come on.
- 喔，慢一点啊，孩子 - 他在另外一头
Just a minute now, boys.
- 走吧 - 好的
But he's on the other side. Come on.
- 走吧 - 等一下
I think this means a whole lot to her.
我认为这对她意义重大
你不晓得这对我有多重要…
You have no idea how much it means to me...
能够安顿下来 过着与世无争的日子
...to be able to settle down to a life of peace and quiet.
我去拿行李
I'll get the luggage.
哈罗，各位！
杰克！
汤姆
帕布洛
齐伯，咱们走吧
Zeb, let's go.
骑警，别告诉我你大老远跑来黄金城 是为了来见我？
Don't tell me you come all the way to Gold City just to meet me?
我根本没想到
I hardly expected it.
这位是美丽的罗林太太？
And the beautiful Mrs. Rawlings?
真是无上荣幸
What a pleasure.
我真嫉妒你，骑警 一个年轻貌美的老婆…
I envy you, Marshal, a well-favored, bright-eyed wife...
就像太阳一般耀眼灿烂
...just as dazzlin' as that sun up there.
让人心存感激，可不是？
It makes you almost thankful, don't it?
让人很想好好活下去
It makes a person wanna live.
再见
Adios.
那是查理葛兰特
That's Charlie Gant.
我以为你说他在蒙大拿州
I thought you said he was in Montana?
齐伯？
Zeb?
我只是去拿行李，没事
I'm just gonna get the luggage, that's all.
你去办入房手续吧，茱莉
See to the rooms, will you, Julie?
- 普莱斯考特，照顾马 - 好的
-Prescott, take care of the horses. -Yes, sir.
- 奈勒斯，去帮你妈妈 - 好的
-Linus, help your mother. -Yes, sir.
什么事不对劲吗，茱莉？
Anything wrong, Julie?
没…没事
No. No, nothing.
走吧，伊芙
Come on, Eve.
- 卢 - 齐伯
有时间吗？
Got a minute?
我当然有时间
Of course, I got a minute.
来…
我郑重劝告你应该要…
- 抽雪茄？ - 不，谢谢
-Cigar? -No, thanks.
有什么事我能帮你呢？
Well, what can I do for you?
你尽管说吧
Go ahead, name it.
我今天早上看到葛兰特下火车
I saw Gant get off the train this morning.
有三个人去接他
There were three men waiting for him.
那是你跑来的原因，是吧？
That's why you're here, huh?
没错
That's it.
我们根本没有任何办法…
Look, there ain't a thing we can do...
阻止查理葛兰特在这地区的活动
...to keep Charlie Gant from goin' where he wants to in this territory.
我知道 我知道他的为人…
I know. I know what he was...
但现在已经结束了
...but that's over now.
这一切早已结束 当他哥哥…
It was over the day his brother got--
那天应该两个都杀的 但是…
You should've killed 'em both that day, but....
但你没有 现在我真的一点办法都没了
Well, you didn't and there ain't a thing I can do about it now.
他来这里做什么，卢？ 你难道不好奇吗？
What's he doin' here, Lou? Ain't you even curious?
你要我怎么做？ 拿枪抵住他把他赶出城？
What do you want me to do? Run him out of town at the point of a gun?
你想我们仍用手枪执行法律？
Do you think it will put the law inside a holster here?
你看那边，齐伯 那才是法律
Look over there, Zeb. There's the law.
那些条文规定才是法律…
With all its writs and decrees and....
- 我们现在隶属巡回法院管辖
We abide by that circuit judge, now.
- 但在此同时有多少人被杀？
How many get killed meantime?
没有人被杀 不会有人被杀  达克哈立戴，克兰顿，杨格斯…
Nobody's got killed. Nobody's goin' to. Doc Halliday, the Clantons, the Youngers....
- 他们全都死了
They're all gone now.
- 查理葛兰特并没死
Charlie Gant ain't gone.
你去弄来拘捕令 我就去抓葛兰特
You get me a warrant. I'll get you Gant.
卢？明天运送黄金的篷车队 需要三名护卫
Lou, they want three guards in the wagon with the gold shipment tomorrow.
- 三名？
Three?
- 是宗大案子，市价超过十万元
This is a big one. Over $100,000 worth.
我带克雷顿和辛姆斯去，好吧？
I'll take Clayton and Sims with me. All right?
怎么样？
Well?
什么怎么样？
Well what?
那对你不代表任何意义吗？
Doesn't that mean anything to you?
- 那代表我们需要派三名护卫 - 在火车上！
-It means we put on a three-man guard. -To the train.
那到时候呢？
What happens then?
我们这里每个月都会运送黄金出去
You know there's gold goin' out of here every month or so.
自从杰西詹姆士被杀之后 再没有火车被劫事件
There hasn't been a train robbery since Jesse James was killed.
如果律师们需要私下会谈 我们可以谈一下
齐伯
我不想惹任何麻烦
I don't want any trouble here, now.
咱们是很久的朋友了
We've been friends a long time.
身为朋友…
As a friend...
我想请你离开这里
...l'd like you to leave town.
孩子们，给我过来！
Boys, get back from there!
你自己往下看
Look down there, son.
你知道这底下有多深吗？
Do you know how deep that shaft is?
有一千尺深
That's 1,000 foot deep.
你知道一千尺有多深吗？
Do you know how deep 1,000 foot is?
如果把两百个弟弟摆在你肩膀上…
If you had 200 brothers, all standin' on your shoulders...
- 你还是看不到最上面
...you wouldn't be able to see over the top.
- 那我不就被压扁了！
I'd be squished.
走吧，我带你们去看发动机
Come on. I'll show you boys the donkey engine.
你们先过去 我马上就来
You boys go ahead. I'll be along in a minute.
（黄金城金矿）听说你跑去找当地骑警谈我的事
I hear you've been talkin' to the local marshal about me.
- 此举可真友善
Would you call that friendly?
- 我从不认为我们的关系是友善的
I never considered us exactly friendly.
我不喜欢你，骑警
I don't like you, Marshal.
我不喜欢你们这种人在这国家 所做的一切
I don't like what you and your kind are doin' to this country.
我不想惹麻烦
I don't want any trouble.
可是你执意要用从前的标准来看 就你和我？
You wanna put things on the old basis, just you and me?
那无所谓
That's fine.
我不打算和你争执，葛兰特
I'm not gonna get in a fight with you, Gant.
那你是想要和平罗，骑警？
It's peace you want, Marshal?
和平？
Peace?
我只知道一种和平
There's only one kind I know of.
就是我哥哥得到的那种
That's the kind my brother's got.
你哥哥的遭遇并没有让你 学到太多教训，是吧？
What happened to your brother didn't teach you very much, did it?
放轻松，骑警…
Easy, Marshal.
佛洛依从未出过差错…
Floyd never made mistakes...
除了那次他误信你…
...except the one time he trusted you.
让你成了漏网之鱼
And you're the one that got away.
总有一天 我会去府上好好拜访你们
One of these days I'm likely to pay you Rawlings' a little visit.
快点！走吧！
把黄金箱子抬上来！
很多黄金
快点，继续搬，各位！
齐伯？
卢莱姆西来了
Lou Ramsey's here.
卢
- 我警告过你，齐伯 - 什么事？
-I warned you, Zeb. -What is it?
葛兰特昨晚跑来找我
Gant came to see me last night.
说你试图找他麻烦
He said you tried to start some trouble with him.
你相信他？
You believe him?
我告诉你，齐伯 你要惹麻烦，到你自己的地盘去搞！
I'm tellin' you, Zeb, you take your trouble to your own territory.
我这里不要有任何麻烦
I don't want any more of it here.
不会有任何麻烦，卢 葛兰特走了
There won't be any more trouble, Lou. Gant's gone.
今天一大早就离开出城了
He rode out of here early this mornin'.
和谁？
With who?
他的道上兄弟
His gang.
他们现在应该在 这里和金曼之间的某个地方…
They should be somewhere between here and Kingman...
等火车出现
...waitin' on that train.
你别想唬我，齐伯
You don't fool me for a minute, Zeb.
你并不是想破抢案 你是想抓葛兰特
You're not lookin' for a robbery, you're lookin' for Gant.
你身上仍有他射你的子弹 那是在德州
You still carry lead where he shot you. That was Texas.
还有在奥克拉荷马你射杀佛洛依 现在换这件事！
And Oklahoma, where you killed Floyd. And now this.
很抱歉，茱莉…
I'm sorry, Julie...
我们局里不要和这件事有关
...but I don't want my office to be any part of this.
齐伯，孩子们已经把东西都准备好了
The boys have got the team hitched.
我知道
I know.
差不多时候该走了
It's almost time to go.
齐伯？
- 茱莉 - 没有人要你去对付葛兰特
No one's askin' you to face Gant.
没有人逼你
No one's makin' you.
我们可以马上离开这里 我们可以忘掉这一切
We could ride out of here right now. We could forget it.
或许你有什么事情没告诉我
Maybe there's somethin' you haven't told me.
是吗，齐伯？
Is there, Zeb?
我求你别去
I'm askin' you not to go.
求求你
Please.
别去
Don't go.
对不起，茱莉…
Sorry, Julie.
再也没有比男人的荣誉感 更顽固的东西
I guess there's nothin' more pigheaded in a man than his sense of honor.
男人全都一个样 每个都是如此
They're all the same, every one of 'em.
就拿我的克里夫来说好了
You take my Cleve now.
他从来不肯错过任何扑克牌局
Never could turn down a poker game.
义无反顾一定要去
He felt duty bound to go.
有时还连玩三个晚上 但他就是不肯罢休…
Three nights runnin' sometimes, but he wouldn't quit, not if his life depended on it.
即便要他的命也一样 他…
我想这一点也不好笑
I guess it isn't very funny.
妈？
Ma!
爸爸呢？
Where's Pa?
- 他出去了 - 妈怎么了？
-Out. That's where he is. -What's the matter with Mom?
没事…来吧…到另一个房间
Nothin's the matter. Come on, now, in the other room.
- 怎么回事？ - 快点，我们想要玩！
Come on, darlin', we're gonna play.
乖女孩…这样才对
That's a good girl. That's better.
- 妈妈怎么了？ - 没怎么
-What's the matter with Mama? -Nothin's the matter.
你们会玩游戏吗？
You know any games?
- 我们会玩捉鬼 - 大风吹！
-We know tag. -Musical chairs.
- 捉鬼 - 我知道躲迷藏
I know hide and seek.
你们会玩扑克牌吗？
-Do you know how to play poker? -Poker?
- 扑克牌？ - 扑克牌？
You're in luck. Get down right there. Now come on, sit down. That's it.
算你们走运，坐下来 过来，坐下，很好
可是我们不会玩扑克牌
But we don't know how to play poker.
所以你们才要学啊
Well, it's time you learned.
首先，我们一人分五张牌…
First, we'll start off with a little five-card stud.
你的来福枪给我，齐伯
I'll take that rifle, Zeb.
还有你的手枪
Your pistol, too.
对不起，卢…
Sorry, Lou.
我无法照做
I just can't oblige.
我以为现在的法律不容许你那样做
I thought the law wouldn't let you use that any more.
如果必要的话 我会那么做
I'll use it if I have to.
我要离开这里，卢 我要带这个走
I'm goin' out of here, Lou, and I'm takin' this with me.
去杀葛兰特！
To kill Gant.
你是那么想的，是吧？
That's what you think, isn't it?
你以为是我和他之间的私事
It's somethin' personal between him and me.
卢，有可能是…
Well, Lou, it could be...
如果我和我的家人安定下来 等他来骚扰我们
...if I settle down with my family and wait for him to come.
他一定会出现的 如果我不现在阻止他的话
And he'll come, if I don't stop him here and now.
我要在葛兰特犯案时 人赃俱获逮住他
I'm gonna catch Gant red-handed, breakin' the law...
然后我要借助法律 让他永远不再得逞
...and then I'm gonna use the law to put him away once and for all.
法律，卢
The law, Lou.
我要借助法律
I'm gonna use the law...
但少了你的帮助 我成功的机率不大！
...but I haven't got much chance without your help.
守车厢里有多少人？
How many men in the caboose?
只有一个煞车手
Just one brakeman.
- 他有没有携带武器？ - 没有，从来没有
Is he armed?
No, never has been.
我会在车厢里
I'll be in the express car.
谢谢你，卢
Thanks.
骑警？
Marshal!
前方有几名骑士
There's some riders up ahead.
我来看一下
I'll take a look.
机师！前面有路障！
Engineer, there's a barricade ahead!
直接冲过去！
Open her up, wide open.
齐伯！
快点！快点！
Come on. Come on.
- 大家都上来了？ - 法兰奇的马跌下去了
Everybody make it?
- 我想他应该没上来 - 咱们开始行动吧
Frenchy's horse fell. I don't think he made it.
要拿到黄金还有一段路
Well, let's move. It's a long way from here to that gold.
没有危险，继续往前走
There's no danger. Just keep goin'.
是罗林
It's Rawlings!
火车往后退！
Back this train up!
快点！
And fast!
（旅馆）
我们为什么这么早就要离开，爸？
How come we're leavin' so early, Pa?
咱们路途遥远呢，儿子
We got a long way to go, son.
来
Here.
姨婆，我们什么时候去你家？
Auntie, when are we going to your house?
到你们家之后 你爸爸会再做决定
Your daddy will decide when we get to your home.
姨婆，可不可以带山姆一起去？
Honest? Can we take Sam with us?
我想是山姆带我们去吧
I think Sam is taking us.
爸，还有多远才到 莉莉丝姨婆的农场？
Pa, how much further is it to Aunt Lilith's ranch?
儿子，过下一个弯之后 再下一个弯…
Well, son, it's around the next bend, and the next bend...
就在山谷后面
...and the valley beyond.
- 莉莉丝姨婆，你知道那首歌？
Aunt Lilith, do you know that song?
- 那是我们的歌
That's our song!
你们的歌？
Your song?
在你爸出生之前 我早已唱过那首歌了
I sang that song long before your pa was ever born.
【走，走，跟我走吧】
"Away, away, come away with me
【那荒野长着野草】
"Where the grass grows wild
【这风在自由的吹】
"Where the winds blow free
【走，走】- 齐伯
"Away, away--" Zeb!
【跟我走吧】
"Come away with me
【我会和你在荒草上安一个家】
"Where I'll build you a home In the meadow
【来吧，来吧，有一片神奇的土地】
"Come, come, there's a wondrous land
【为了充满希望的心】
"For the hopeful heart
【荒野乐意帮助】
"For the willing hand
【来吧，来吧 ，有一片神奇的土地】
"Come, come, there's a wondrous land
【我将在这里为你在草地上建一个家】
"And I'll build you a home in the meadow."
西部就是被这些已不在人世的 先锋者，拓荒者和冒险家赢来的
The West that was won by its pioneers, settlers, adventurers is long gone now.
但它却永远属于他们
Yet, it is theirs forever.
他们在历史上留下痕迹 从未被风雨侵袭消失…
For they left tracks in history that will never be eroded by wind or rain...
从未被耕耘机碾平过 从未被堆肥淹没过
...never plowed under by tractors, never buried in the compost of events.
从他们简单纯朴的生活方式 他们强韧的生命力…
Out of the hard simplicity of their lives, out of their vitality...
他们的希望与悲伤…
...their hopes and their sorrows...
衍生出勇气与荣耀的传奇…
...grew legends of courage and pride...
启发他们的孩子以及后辈子孙
...to inspire their children and their children's children.
从他们血汗孕育过的土地…
From soil enriched by their blood...
和他们探索与创造的热忱…
...out of their fever to explore and build...
曾经炙热的沙漠如今变成大湖…
...came lakes where once were burning deserts...
发展出丰硕的大地 矿产以及麦田…
...came the goods of the earth, mines and wheat fields...
果园和伟大的伐木园…
...orchards and great lumber mills...
这一切便是打造这国家的力量
...all the sinews of a growing country.
从他们简陋的落脚之处，杂货店 演变成城市…
Out of their rude settlements, their trading posts, came cities...
甚至成为全世界顶尖的大城市
...to rank among the great ones of the world.
这一切传承让人们享有梦想的自由…
All the heritage of a people free to dream...
行动的自由
...free to act...
让人们能自由自在开创自己的命运
...free to mold their own destiny.
乐土，乐土
"The promised land, promised land
乐土是鱼米之乡，有丰富的黄金
"Promised land The land of plenty, rich with gold
这里是梦想家用拳头和枪书写的
"Here came dreamers With Bible, fist and gun
他们的马车穿过平原的土地
"Bound for land Across the plains their wagons rode
抽打着皮鞭飞驰
"Hell bent for leather
这就是赢得西部的方式
"That's how the West was won
他们肩并肩驯服野蛮的大草原
"Side by side They tamed the savage prairie land
没有什么能阻止他们，没有风，没有雨，也没有太阳
"Nothing stopped them Nor wind, nor rain, nor sun
每一块土地的每一个先锋
"Side by side Each pioneer from every land
所有的土地都拉扯在一起
"All pulled together
这就是赢得西部的方式
"That's how the West was won
他们歌唱的时候将放下他们的脚步
"And they sang of the day When they would rest their boots
在这片水域流动的土地上
"In a land where the still waters flowed
有人有与妻子落地生根的梦想
"There were dreams of man and wife Who'd put down roots
他们的爱和爱的种子会在这成长
"And their love and the seeds of love Would grow
剧终
（退场）